字幕制作｜猫科夫
Subtitles: Mokov
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
25周年庆典表演　爱德华王子剧院　2014年9月22日
西贡小姐
我们当中，会出现一位“西贡小姐”
One of us will be Miss Saigon
我重说一遍！是“西贡，小姐”
I spread the word, it's Miss Saigon
- 谁离开了？谁还没有走？ - 别多管闲事，把你的裤子给我穿上！
- Who's left in town? Who hasn't gone?  - Shut up and get your hot pants on
- 街上的大兵越来越少了  - 他们走了，我们能活下去吗？
- Each day more GI's disappear  - Will we survive when no-one's here?
你们必须要相信我这个“工程师”！
You girls must trust your Engineer
我今天带来一个惊喜，过来！
I have a little surprise for you. Come here. Hey!
我在村里发现了这个姑娘，还是个闺女！
I found this new girl from the country, untouched
给她扮上！
Get her ready
我来教教这个雏儿怎么放松！
I'd give that virgin act a rest
你得学会说“你是我的第一个美国客人”
You are my first American
让开让开！整天这样你们不累吗？
alley, alley! Why does it take all day?
把你们的屁股都洗干净！今晚要开张了！
Get your asses on stage, I'm raising cash tonight
我们当中，会出现一位“西贡小姐”
One of us will be Miss Saigon
西贡的风声紧了好几个礼拜了
They say Saigon has weeks
- 你们各就各位  - 今晚，我就是“西贡小姐”
- I say it's time to pack  - Tonight I must be Miss Saigon
这些臭娘们变得越来越没用了！
Each night these little buns of theirs are worth less and less
我得赶紧捞一笔，买个绿卡一走了之
I need a visa fast and I'm not looking back
他娘的，大兵们来了
Son of a bitch, they're here
我还能干我的老本行
I can still engineer
乔伊先生，这边请！
Monsieur Joey, please, come inside
就像往常一样，我的小荡妇们
It's like the old days,my little gamines
- 没问题  - 去看看谁来了？
- Oh, sure  - Just look who's in there
- 陆战队的大兵！ - 来了吗？
- A gang of Marines  - They're here?
咱们要把他们榨干！
We'll pick 'em clean
- 今晚就专心做这一件事  - 扯淡！
- That's what tonight's all about  - Bullshit!
没准哪个大兵就能把你带走
One of these boys might be your ticket out
- 把这衣服脱下来  - 哇哦
- Get out of that dress  - Wow.
嘿，瞧瞧
No, wait
- 这是我新的小宝贝儿嘛！ - 啥！
- It's my new princess  - What?
- 小宝贝儿？ - 你他妈的在跟我开玩笑！
- Princess?  - Are you fucking kidding me?
雏儿，能卖个好价钱
A virgin will give them a treat
闭嘴！
Shut up!
闭上眼睛，享受吧
Lower your eyelids and play sweet
男人们都喜欢在晚上找新新鲜刺激
Men pay the moon to get fresh meat
新鲜也就新鲜一次！别吵了，别吵了！
Fresh is only fresh once alley, alley
排好队，摆好姿势
Line up and do your song
别让人家等的太久
Don't make the show too long
好戏开场啦！
Voile! On stage, all
欢迎来到，追梦国度！
Welcome to Dreamland!
西贡的夜晚性感火爆
The heat is on in Saigon
姑娘们等着我们来搞
The girls are ready to screw
她们当中的一位会成为“西贡小姐”
One of these slits here will be Miss Saigon
当我们无法突破防线，猜猜我们会做什么？
And since we're stuck here in hell, what's a soldier to do?
这里臭气连天，结束战争就是个谎言
The stink is making me choke! Turns out this war is a joke
而忘掉谎言却只能靠自己
Turns out the joke is on you
嘿，克里斯先生，约翰先生，这儿有个新来哒！
Hey, Monsieur Chris, Monsieur John, a gift
我知道你们来这儿是为了西贡小姐
You've come to win Miss Saigon
你请客？
You brought him
我请我的哥们来度过他难忘的一夜
I gotta get my friend laid as a last souvenir
别废话了，我的兴致已经到这儿了
I love you, pal, but your bullshit I've had up to here
西贡的夜晚性感火爆
The heat is on in Saigon
反正我们还没撤离，我来给你找个姑娘
But till they tell us we're gone,I'm gonna buy you a girl
- 来杯啤酒就行了  - 搞起来！
- You can buy me a beer  - It's showtime!
来自湄公河口，海防的姑娘！
From Haiphong to the Mekong Delta,
请容我把西贡最美的姑娘隆重介绍给你！
may I present the most beautiful girls in Saigon!
- 蜜蜜！ - 看我性感比基尼！
- Mimi  - See my bikini
- 尺码不大不小正好！ - 伊薇特！
- It's just the right size  - Yvette
我的大腿还合你胃口吗？
Don't you enjoy how it rides up my thighs?
- 多米尼卡！ - 看看我的身段
- Dominique  - Look from behind
- 绝对惊爆眼球！ - 伊万妮！
- It'll knock out your eyes  - Yvonne
我是战场上最致命的武器！
I'll show you my special trophy of war
- 菲菲！ - 陆战队的大兵们，看看我的活儿！
- Fifi  - For a Marine I'll show more
我都浑身发软了！
You won't get up off the floor
西贡的夜晚性感火爆
The heat is on in Saigon
别让我离开，这些小妞都美极了
Don't tell me I'm reassigned, all that chickenshit sucks
今晚我要纵情享受，十美元就能玩儿个够
Tonight I'm out of my mind, not to mention ten bucks
你们熟知的！河内最性感的妞儿！
You all know her as the sex toy from Hanoi.
陈万姬小姐！
Miss Gig Van Tran.
如果我是你的梦中情人，我能让你神魂颠倒
If I'm your pin-up, I'll melt all your brass
把我的照片挂上墙，图钉按在我的屁股上
Stuck on the wall with a pin in my ass
如果你搞上了我，你就坐上了头等舱
If you get me, you will travel first class
我还让你知道，我有魔力
I'll show you, we'll make magic, Cherie
来来来！买票入场就有机会免费玩儿姑娘啦！
You buy more tickets from me, the winner gets her for free
西贡的肉体是如此卑贱！
The meat is cheap in Saigon
我已经心灰意冷，娼妇也许能唤醒我
I used to love getting stoned, waking up with some whore
我不知道为什么这样，我感觉很失落
I don't know why I went dead, it's not fun any more
乡下的干净姑娘怎么样？
How about something fresh from the country?
原装没动，原封原样的，小金！
Legs unpasted, parts uncharted. Kim.
我今年十七岁，我刚到这里
I'm 17 and I'm new here today
我来自遥远的农村乡下
The village I come from seems so far away
这里的姑娘都比我会说话
All of these girls here know much more what to say
但是我知道，我该如何展现自己
But I know I'm so much more than you see
我有无数的梦想
A million dreams are in me
天哪，约翰，她是谁？
Jesus, John, who is she?
参谋部眉头紧皱
The Cong is tightening the noose
谁知道明天我能否活着？
Is it a week or a day or an hour we got?
今晚就是最后的一晚，不用白不用！
Tonight could be our last shot, got to put it to use
宝贝儿，我兴致高昂，你能否满足？
I've got a fever, babe, and you're gonna catch it
宝贝儿，我有个地方不舒服，你能否平复？
I got an itch, and, baby, you'd better scratch it
蜜蜜、万姬、伊薇特还是伊万妮
Mimi, Gig, Yvette or Yvonne
给我来扎啤酒！跟西贡小姐共度美好时光！
Gonna buy me a beer! Here's to you, Miss Saigon
伊薇特！伊万妮！
Yvonne! Yvette!
菲菲！蜜蜜！小金！
Fifi! Mimi! Kim!
还有万姬！
And Gig!
注意，下面就要宣布了
Attention, sail vouch plait.
根据投票！陈万姬小姐当选为今晚的“西贡小姐”！
By popular demand, Miss Gig Van Tran is tonight's Miss Saigon.
西贡的夜晚性感火爆
The heat is on in Saigon
我怎能拒绝这气息？
How'd we get used to the smell?
我们不要浪费时光，一波未平，一波又起
So let's get wasted, get high and get laid
- 稳操胜券  - 鬼门关前的告别狂欢
- Shoo-hew!  - A goodbye party in hell
现在，公布抽奖结果！
And now, who wins my little pussycat?
六十六号顾客！
Number 66!
谁来照顾你宝贝？
Who takes care of you, baby?
就是你嘛，带我去美国怎么样？
You do, but will you take me to America?
又来了，现在不行！
Come on. Not right now. Damn!
我能当个好太太
Hey! I'll make a good wife.
- 我说了，不行！ - 你这混蛋！
- I said no!  - You prick!
- 让我来，让我来  - 都是胡诌八扯！
- Let me take care of this.  - This is bullshit!
别跟我整没用的！
Don't fuck with me.
- 没事了，没事了，万姬只是有点累了  - 神经病
- It's OK. Gig, she likes it rough.  - Crazy, man.
来来，再喝点酒，再找个姑娘
Come on, drink some more. Play with the girls.
满屋嘈杂，恶语相加
They are not nice, they're mostly noise
他们赌咒发誓时像条汉子、胡搞起来却是个孩子
They swear like men, they screw like boys
他们根本就没有良心
I know there's nothing in their hearts
每一次我揽他入怀
But every time I take one in my arms
就开始
It starts
脑海里的幻影浮现
The movie in my mind
他们抛给我们的梦想
The dream they leave behind
我无法忘怀
A scene I can't erase
每当士兵们抱住我，我就想
And in a strong GI's embrace
逃离这种生活
Flee this life
逃离这种地方
Flee this place
连篇的幻影来来去去
The movie plays and plays
我要找到终身相许
I'll find my true romance
他带我远走高飞
He takes me to a place
去一个不用跳舞地方
Where I don't have to dance
我给他生儿育女
Our children laugh all day
但现在我已经不抱希望了
But all that I've been through
梦想已经不能成真了
Can't make my dream come true
梦想啊！
Dream
我苦苦追寻的梦想啊！
The dream I long to find
只是连篇的幻影
The movie in my mind
我已经不会哭，已经麻木
I will not cry, I will not think
我只能继续跳舞，继续给他们灌酒
I'll do my dance, I'll make them drink
强颜欢笑的，那并不是我
When I make love, it won't be me
他们的踢打
And if they hurt me
我只是闭上眼睛顺受
I'll just close my eyes and see
满屋嘈杂，恶语相加
They are not nice, they're mostly noise
只有连篇的幻影
The movie in my mind
他们屠戮时是条汉子，倒下时又是个孩子
They kill like men, they die like boys
我们的梦想也来来去去
The dream that fills my head
他们大把的给钱，却从来不关心
They give their cash, they keep their hearts
一个未曾沾上献血的人
A man who will not kill
日复一日、夜复一夜
But every night again it starts
他会为我挺身而出吗？
He'll fight for me instead
这样的男人只会在军营里恐惧
He'll keep the fear at bay
更不可能在晚上出现在这里
So no one comes at night
把我的梦吹散了吧！
To blow the dream away
梦啊！
Dream
我必须要找到的梦啊！
The dream I have to find
就算只是连篇的幻影！
The movie in my mind
- 嘿，宝贝儿，来啊  - 嘿！
- Hey, baby, come here.  - Hey!
每当大兵们抱住我，我就想
And in a strong GI's embrace
逃离这生活
Flee this life
逃离这地方
Flee this place
在那遥远的世界
A world that's far away
生活不会如此的不堪
Where life is not unkind
虽然只是连篇的幻影
The movie in my mind
真感人啊，好了好了，赶快回去接客！
alleluia, alley, get back to work. Now'.!
- 别烦我  - 嘿，约翰先生
- Come on, man.  - Hey, Monsieur John.
你想不想发财呢？风风光光的回家？
How would you like to get rich? Go home in style?
- 谁不想啊？怎么说？ - 那就好
- Yeah, OK, what's the pitch?  - Yeah.
一张美国绿卡，你开个价
A US visa to help me get out
只需要你去大使馆运作一下
Lend me a bit of your embassy clout, you dig, baby?
现在绝对不可能了，你比我清楚
There isn't a chance, pal, you're too well known
或者，你把那个穿裙子的姑娘给我
Look, what I want is that girl in the dress
眼光不错老兄，她是小金
You have a good eye, her name is Kim
她是我新的姑娘
She's my new princess
你来试试她？
You give her a try
伙计，天哪！这太阳是从哪边出来了？
My buddy, Chris, it's like something just snapped
她可是人人都想要的，她身上可是有宝贝啊
She's what he needs, she's got treasures untapped
但是我必须事先警告你，她可不便宜
But I have to warn you, she don't come cheap
没问题，伙计
I got that covered, my man.
- 她，要卖二十美元！ - 她？就她？二十美元？
- It's got to be 20 for my princess  - 20 for this shit?
她可是个雏儿！啊…不好，说漏嘴了
She's sort of a virgin... well, more or less
- 您拿着  - 再拿二十块我就给你开个房间
- You take it.  - For 20 more you get a room and key
你耍我！
Don't fuck me, man!
五十块钱就能和她待上一整夜
For 50 bucks, she's got the whole night free
“工程师”推荐的姑娘准备错！
No one gives you a buzz like the Engineer does
你来几个人都可以
You may share if you like.
别太羡慕我，伙计，你熊了
Stop drooling, white boy, you're losing your cool
- 她太引人犯罪了  - 约翰，你冷静点！
- You like this jail bait?  - John, open your eyes
这太过分了！简直不可救药！
This is the end of the line, this whole rotten scene
她可是个好货啊！你这是怎么了？
She's good, man. What? Come on!
这是个小姑娘，我们会受处分的
This little girl, we could be in the sack
我知道，放开！
I know, man
而且我不能做出格的事情
And I would take something I can't give back
该回去了，该远离这个肮脏的地方了
It's time to go home, it's time to get clean
不不不
No, no, no
没想到你这么纯情，我都快哭了
I'm starting to cry, you're so out of touch
你就是想得太多，顾忌太多
The trouble with you is you think too much
- 别碰我  - 一个娼妇总好过寂寞的床
- Get the fuck off of me!  - A whore is better than an empty bed
你需要放松一下才能知道你需要什么
Man, you need some action to fill your head
别犹豫了，工程师说的准没错！
Nothing gives you a hit like the Engineer's shit
说的太对了！
That's right
我们走，离开这里
Let's get out of here. Let's go!
我的小宝贝儿，我猜对了
My little princess, I was right
你是今晚最成功的交易
You are the first to score tonight
你今天就盯着他
You caught that sergeant by the nose
在那个中士离开前哪都别去
You stay with him until he goes
叫他克里斯，他喜欢
Call him Chris, he'll like that
- 求求你，不要……  - 你说你想干活儿，这就是活儿！
- Please, don't  - You said you needed a job
你说过你会接客！
You said you'd turn a trick
你最好照你说的做，快点！
You better prove it, and quick
克里斯先生
Monsieur Chris?
别担心，我刚刚亲手给她洗过澡…哈哈哈
Don't worry, she's clean. I washed her myself.
来，音乐！
Look at that. Music.
她是个非常好的姑娘，交给别人我可不放心
She's a very good girl. I'll give her to somebody else.
- 你滚开！ - 好的，宝贝儿
- You fuck off.  - All right, baby.
约翰先生！吹个高调儿哒！
Monsieur John! Hit the high note!
我叫小金
My name is Kim
我喜欢你，克里斯
I like you, Chris
- 别这么说  - 那该怎么说？
- Don't talk like that.  - What did I say?
你不应该在这种地方！
You shouldn't be here.
拿着这个，赶紧离开！
Just take this and get the hell out of here.
- 真他妈的……  - 嘿，怎么了？
- Goddamn it.  - Hey. What's going on?
- 你不喜欢她吗？ - 哦，不，我喜欢
- You don't like her?  - Oh, yes, I do
我也喜欢他
I like him too
那就带她离开啊？
Take her away, come on, man
带我走吧
Take me away
求求你别说别的，带我走吧
Please, don't say a word, just come with me
好了，好了，现在该交钱了，你们这些吊儿郎当的大兵们
All right, it's time to pay up, you horny bastards.
谢谢你，托尼先生
Thank you, Monsieur Tony.
越早交钱，越早快活，你不会不想快活吧？
The sooner you pay, the sooner you come, and you want to come, right?
这是给我的？谢谢你，泰克斯，好好享受
Is that mine? Thank you, Tex. Enjoy that one.
嘿，底特律小伙子，你是不是忘了什么？
Hey, Detroit, you're forgetting something.
记得洗干净手
Wash your fingers.
约翰先生，你身上的这个可不老实，可别让她咬喽，哈哈哈
Monsieur John, this one doesn't scratch.She bites.
工程师，这可是支不错的雪茄
Engineer? A touch of class, man.
- 那我留着到美国再抽  - 你随便啦，到时候给我弄个姑娘就行
- I'll smoke this when I get to America.  - Whatever, man. Got me a lady.
晚安我的小心肝儿们
Sweet dreams, my princess.
为何西贡的夜如此不安
Why does Saigon never sleep at night?
这姑娘的身上为什么有橘子的香气
Why does this girl smell of orange trees?
我行差踏错，感觉如此堕落
How can I feel good when nothing's right?
为何天气闷热她却如此平静？
Why is she cool when there is no breeze?
越南啊
Vietnam
你从来不给出答案
You don't give answers,do you, friend?
我只能不停的追问
Just questions that don't ever end
神啊，这是为什么！
Why, God?
为什么是此时此刻
Why today?
我已经不能回头
I'm all through here
只能走下去
On my Way
这个地方没有什么我还能失去的了
There's nothing left here that I'll miss
为何要给我留下这样的一个夜晚
Why send me now a night like this?
那床榻上的姑娘是谁
Who is the girl in this rusty bed?
为什么我还不离开这个龌龊的房间
Why am I back in a filthy room?
为什么她的声音还在我心中萦绕
Why is her voice ringing in my head?
为什么让我沉醉于她身上劣质的香水味
Why am I high on her cheap perfume?
越南啊！
Vietnam
我知道你没有对我设防
Hey, look, I mean you no of fence
但为什么现在发生的事情如此费解
But why does nothing here make sense?
神啊，这是为什么！
Why, God?
求祢伸出手
Show your hand
为什么我不懂
Why can't one guy understand?
为什么我和一个陌生的姑娘要经历这些
I've been with girls who knew much more
我从未如此困惑
I've never felt confused before
为什么是我！
Why me?
祢有什么安排
What's your plan?
我帮不了她
I can't help her
没人能！
No one can
我想抹掉这段记忆
I want my memories as they were
但是现在如何也无法抹去
But now I'll leave remembering her
别挡路
Get out of my...
躲开！
Out Of my way!
在我回家之后，没人会讨论这场战争
When I went home before, no one talked of the war
他们从电视上知道的根本就不是我经历过的
What they knew from TV didn't have a thing to do with me
滚开！
Get out of here!
我要回去战斗，因为西贡已经彻底腐朽
I went back and re-upped, sure, Saigon is corrupt
即便退伍后只能在使馆开车
It felt better to be here driving for the embassy
只要多救一些人出去
Cos here if you can pull a string
才能让我重新感到好受
A guy like me lives like a king
放下一切，别去伤脑筋！
Just as long as you don't believe anything
坏了
Shit.
嘿，大兵哥，你能带我离开这里吗？
Hey, GI.Can you help me get out of here?
- 我帮不了你  - 我有钱！
- I can't help you.  - I've got money.
我不要你的钱！我不要你的钱！
I don't need your money. I don't need your money.
神啊！为什么！
Why, God?
为什么是她
Why this face?
为何战乱中她如此美丽
Why such beauty in this place?
我想抹掉这段记忆
I want my memories as they were
但是现在如何也无法抹去
But now I'll leave remembering her
只有她！
Just her
他妈的……
Fuck!
这些钱给你
This money's yours
拜托，拿着吧
Please, take it all
- 不够吗？ - 不不，我不想要别的
- Hey, you want more?  - No, no, I don't want anything
- 你有毛病吗？ - 我以前没做过
- What's wrong with you?  - I've not done this before
别骗人了
That can't be true
我为什么要骗你？
Why would I lie?
这里所有的姑娘都说谎，唯一的目的就是离开这里
Look, all the girls lie, they just want to get out of here
也许你不是那样的姑娘，但是又怎么知道呢？
Maybe you're not like that, but I don't know who you are
混蛋……
Fuck!
你想听听我这个越南姑娘的故事吗？
Do you want one more tale of a Vietnam girl?
你想听听被包办婚姻是什么滋味吗？
Want to know I was bound to a man I don't love?
抱歉，不想
I'm sorry.
或者你想知道我的村庄是如何化为灰烬的？
Do you want to be told how my village was burned?
还有我的家人如何被炸得粉身碎骨？
Want to hear how my family was blasted away?
你想知道我如何看他们化为一团火焰？
How I ran from the rice fields and saw them in flames?
还有我的父母的尸首如何面目全非？
How my parents were bodies whose faces were gone?
我的心中充满痛苦
I have had my fill of pain
我不敢回想
I will not look back again
因为我早就应该死了！
I would rather die!
今晚我能来找你吗？
Can I see you tonight?
可以，我就在俱乐部
Well, I'll be at the club
逢场作戏，强颜欢笑
Selling beau coup amour
不！不！你不必这样
No. No, you won't.
你应该
How would you like...?
我应该怎样？
How would I like...?
你跟我在一起吧！
How would you like staying with me?
这样我能好受点
It feels right like this
我们就应该在一起
So that's how we should be
你答应吗？
So, would you like?
是的，我答应
Yes, I would like
好的，不说别的了，就这么说定了
OK, it's set, no more to say
那个混蛋的工程师！
Screw the Engineer!
你是我在这里遇到的唯一的美好
You're the one good thing that I've found out here
你是阳光
You are sunlight
我是月亮
And I, moon
被命运眷顾
Joined by the gods of fortune
在子夜和正午
Midnight and high noon
照耀着天空
Sharing the sky
彼此眷顾
One and the same
你和我
You and I
你在这里
You are here
像个奇迹
Like a mystery
我来自一个
I'm from a world
和你如此不同的世界
That's so different from all that you are
黑夜沐浴着光芒
How in the light of one night
我们如此接近
Did we come so far?
外边，天将破晓
Outside, day starts to dawn
你的月亮却还挂在当空
Your moon still floats on high
- 鸟儿们惊醒了  - 星星还在闪耀
- The birds awake  - And the stars shine true
- 我的手还在抖  - 我紧紧抓住！
- My hands still shake  - I reach for you
我们一起在天空相遇
And we meet in the sky
你是阳光
You are sunlight
而我是月亮
And I, moon
在一起
Joined here
用爱的火焰
Brightening the sky
照亮
With the flame
天空
Of love
我们是阳光
We are sunlight
也是月亮
Moonlight
明晚是满月
Tomorrow night will be the full moon
我带朋友们来一起庆祝
I can bring friends to bless our love
好的
OK.
带着纸折的龙和香水
With paper dragons and perfume
如果你愿意的话
If you want me to
- 龙？ - 对
- Dragons?  - Yes.
可以
Sure.
约翰，听见了吗？听着！
John, is that you, buddy?Listen to me
我现在特别激动，因为
Do I sound different? That's how it should be
因为昨晚，我度过了难忘的一夜
Last night, I spent a whole lifetime in paradise
告诉连长，把我的假期都调过来
Tell the CO I'm taking all of my leave
约翰，我们要去玩了，这感觉就像圣诞节
We're going to play house, John, it's like Christmas Eve
我们要连续狂欢四十八个小时
We have sworn we won't see the sun for 48 hours
你在说什么？你疯了吗？
What are you saying? Are you out of your mind?
所有的假期都取消了，以后再说不行吗？
All leave is canceled,you could be left behind
西贡现在已经支离破碎了
Saigon is falling apart and you'd better be here
把你们的手续都准备好！
Please have your papers ready!
在你找乐子的时候事情已经变化了
Here is the news since you've been on the moon
我们在森林外围的战区都失陷了
Cities in the boondocks are dropping like flies
家属和平民都要撤离了
Wives and civilians will be shipping out soon
使馆外面的人群拥挤，他们焦急万分
Crowds around the embassy have tears in their eyes
（译者注：指南越阮文绍政权）
南越政权的总统已经辞职，政府现在根基不稳！
Thieu has resigned, the new regime may not hold
人们聚集在使馆旁边期待我们陆战队的保护
People at the palace think we'll send the Marines
我们承诺的东西一样都没送到
We are sending nothing from what I've been told
- 老弟，你还在吗？ - 在！
- Buddy, are you there?  - Yes!
你听懂了吗？你可真会找节骨眼啊！
Do you know what that means? Sure, time to fall in love!
约翰！仔细听着，你没接过这个电话
John, listen fast,you did not get this call
毕竟是你把我领到那里的
You're the one who bought the girl for me, after all
既然你拿我当朋友，那就帮我帮到底
Once you are a friend, you're a friend through and through
我欠你个情，将来要还的
When you were in trouble, man, I covered for you
这次可不行！现在战事吃紧！可没时间理你那妓女！
Not this time, the town's too hot for one Kong whore
听我的伙计，我不会害你
OI' buddy, I will not get you killed
她可不是个妓女，你我都知道
She is no whore, all right? You saw her too
她更像是一轮，早春的明月
She's really more like... the April moon
- 早个什么他妈的月亮！ - 她的父母都死了
- April fucking moon?  - Both her parents died
她现在孤身一人
She was all alone, she was terrified
多感人的故事，专门忽悠你这样的人
Sweet as that and she's an orphan too How can a guy fight that?
你就只有一天假期，不是两天，快给我回来！
You've got one day, not two, then be back
- 克里斯先生，你迟到了  - 坏了！
- Monsieur Chris, you're late.  - Shit!
怎么了？她把你伺候了一晚上？
What, she kept you up all night?
虽然我们已经谈好了价钱
We had a deal for Kim, but that's on ice
但我必须遗憾的告诉你，我得涨价了
I'm sorry, Sergeant, but I've changed the price
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
我需要一张你们大使馆的通行证
I need a visa from your embassy
你只要把那个给我，这姑娘就归你了
Hey? You give me that, you get the girl for free
别扯没用的了，我只能给你钱
Look, cut the crap, this money's all I've got
我不是发卡的，你听明白了吗？
I don't give visas out, is this a deal or not?
- 听明白了吗？ - 啊，混蛋
- You tell me  - Ah, shit
- 好、好，给钱就行，给钱就行  - 成交
- OK, OK, the money, it will do  - Down
真倒霉，瞧，我还有一块瑞士手表，你也拿去吧
Too bad, I had a Rolex watch for you,it's yours, take it.
我再想想别的办法就好了嘛
I'll get my papers in another way.
我去找个有钱的大佬，你这混蛋！
I'll make a rich man of some attach, you asshole!
跟他耍点花样，然后骗他一票
With little shits like him, you take the bucks and run
他给了我六个礼拜的收入，我只需要一周的就够了
He gave me six weeks' income, I'll be gone in one
下次再让我见到你，我就废了你，你这混蛋！
I'll castrate you next time I see you, you little fuck.
我们当中的一个姑娘就要远行了
One of us girls is moving on
一个姑娘就要离开西贡了
One girl will get out of Saigon
她才是真正的西贡小姐
So look who's really Miss Saigon
她将离开这个不堪的生活
She'll leave this wasted life behind
她将不再只有连篇的幻想
She'll live the movie in my mind
我们到了
They're here!
- 嘘！ - 惊喜！
- Shh!  - Surprise!
看他给她买的新衣服
Look how he bought her a new dress
你肯定在他身上下了功夫
You did a job on him, I guess
他只是问我，我答应了
He simply asked me, I said "yes"
啊，真好
Yeah, right
来吧，祝福我们的新姐妹
Come on, let's bless the new princess
对，那就是我，行了
Yeah, that's me. Get off.
嘿！把鞋脱掉
Hey! Shoes off.
Dju vui vay
yu doi my
vao nyay moy
你是否会对我今后的生活微笑
Will you who gave me life smile today?
并且眷顾这个男人
Look with favoring eyes on this man
从你极乐的国度降下仁慈和宽恕
Show your daughter's heart your forgiveness
And send to us from your home above
你祝福我们的爱
Your blessing on our love
Dju vui vay
yu doi my
vao nyay moy
Dju vui vay
唱的真好听，是什么意思呢？
It's pretty, but what does it mean?
Dju vui vay
我们这里的姑娘在婚礼上唱的
It's what all the girls sing at weddings
- 啥？ - 她们也不会什么别的歌了
- What?  - They didn't know what else to sing
vao nyay moy
这是我听过的最动人的歌声
It's the prettiest thing that I have ever heard
姑娘们！
Hey, girls!
- 为西贡小姐欢呼！ - 西贡小姐！
- To Miss Saigon.  - Miss Saigon!
你在这儿！
You're here, at last
终于找到你了，我带你回家
I've come to take you home
我在夜间偷偷穿过了封锁线
I hid all night, I tunneled through the line
小金，跟我走吧，一起逃离这个无耻的地方
Kim, come with me, we'll flee this shameful place
美国人完蛋了，我们胜利了，我们可以在一起了
They're done, we'll win, you're safe and you are mine
- 嘿！那姑娘是我的！ - 你的？
- Hey! This girl is mine  - Yours?
- 你是谁？ - 住手！
- Now who are you?  - Stop
这头美国猪是谁？
Who is this man, this American pig
跟你在一起的都是些什么人？
Who I now find with you in this place?
你为什么待在这个淫窝里？
Why are you here with these flea-bitten whores?
你也跟她们一样涂脂抹粉了吗？
Do you wear the same paint on your face?
- 滚开！ - 你现在不能呆在这里
- Get out!  - You have no right to be here
我不是你的物件！
I'm not a prize you can claim
我们虽然在十三岁定了亲
We were promised at 13
但是现在的我已经不是从前的我了
The woman I've become is not the same
我们的父亲给我们定的亲事
Our fathers bound us together
你为什么就不能等？
Why couldn't you wait?
你知道我一定会去找你，现在说这些太迟了！
You knew I'd come back to get you! It isn't too late
在你投奔北越的时候，我爹妈就死了
My parents got themselves killed in the week you changed sides
如果他们答应你了，那你现在去找他们吧！
If there were promises, all of them died when they died
别打扰我们了
Shaw's over, pal.
- 小金！你给我躲开！ - 到我身后！
- Kim, leave this man behind  - Stay here
你开枪吧！
No! Go on
开枪吧！
And shoot!
我意已决！
I will not change my mind
- 你还是我的  - 不再是了
- You are still mine  - Not anymore
- 我们至死不渝！ - 你躲开她！
- You're mine until we die  - Get off of her!
西贡完蛋了！
Saigon is doomed
你的大兵也完蛋了
And so is your GI
她会跟我走
She'll leave with me
你违背了你爹的承诺！
You broke your father's word
这就是你永恒的咒诅！
This is your curse
滚出去！
Get out!
派对搞砸了
What a party that was
你必须要离开了
You're going to leave me now
对，我是要离开
Yes, I'm going to leave
但是要带你一起走
And take you out with me
这地方不容我们去感受
In a place that won't let us feel
这生活不容我们寻找真实
In a life where nothing seems real
我找到了你
I have found you
这个世界变幻莫测
In a world that's moving too fast
这个世界没有什么能够永恒
In a world where nothing can last
我会紧紧抱住你
I will hold you
当明天来临，我们的生活会不一样
Our lives will change when tomorrow comes
今夜我们心跳如战鼓敲响
Tonight our hearts drown the beating drums
那我们就歌唱吧
And we'll have music, all right
歌声划破黑暗
Tearing the night
我们的歌声
Our song
只有一把孤独的萨克斯风
Played on a solo saxophone
尖戾的歌声
A crazy sound
寂寞的歌声
A lonely sound
哭泣的讲述着我们永不停歇的爱情
A cry that tells us love goes on and on
只有一把孤独的萨克斯风
Played on a solo saxophone
它告诉我要紧紧的和你相拥
It's telling me to hold you tight
如同在世界末日开始的舞动
And dance like it's the last night of the world
就在地球的另一边
On the other side of the Earth
你的生命将会不同
There's a place your life will have worth
我会带着你
I will take you
你会带着我
I'll go with you
你不会相信你所见到的！
You won't believe all the things you'll see
但我陪你看到的都是真实的
I know cos you'll see them all with me
如果我们在一起，我们就还会奏响
If we're together, that's when we'll hear it again
我们的歌曲
Our song
只有一把孤独的萨克斯风
Played on a solo saxophone
尖戾的歌声
A crazy sound
寂寞的歌声
A lonely sound
凄凉的讲述着我们永不停歇的爱情
A cry that tells us love goes on and on
只有一把孤独的萨克斯风
Played on a solo saxophone
它告诉我要紧紧的和你相拥
It's telling me to hold you tight
如同在世界末日开始的舞动
And dance like it's the last night of the world
我从没梦到过的美梦
Dreams were all I ever knew
有我就能成就的美梦
Dreams you won't need when I'm through
无论哪，我和你
Anywhere we may be
我都会与你相拥
I will sing with you
我们的歌曲
Our song
你去哪里？
Where are you going?
只有一把孤独的萨克斯风
Played on a solo saxophone
现在紧紧的和你相拥
So stay with me and hold me tight
如同在世界末日开始的
And dance like it's the last night
舞动
Of the world
听！它在悄悄的靠近
On silent feet it came
它有着烈焰的吐息
Breathing a sheet of flame
它来了！
It came
它带来猎杀的血腥
Closing in on its rightful prey
它的火焰要燃烧一个世纪
Burning a hundred years away
红色巨龙苏醒了！它散播着宇宙真理！
The morning of the dragon, truth lit up the street
真理如猛虎悄悄的接近
The tiger we were stalking walked on paper feet
它用火焰染红黎明的天际
And in the clear white heat of dawn
把政权夺取
Was gone
- 我们的枪声遍地  - 胜利！
- With guns from every shore  - Victory
- 人民军队的游击  - 胜利！
- The People's Army waged a war  - Victory
- 树林就是我们的阵地  - 胜利！
- Tunneling underneath the trees  - Victory
- 我们从暗处出击  - 红色巨龙的黎明！
- Bringing the giant to its knees  - The morning of the dragon
- 堡垒轰然倒塌  - 宇宙真理遍地开花！
- All the walls fell down  - Truth lit up the street
同志们好啊！
Brother greeted brother
真理如猛虎悄悄的接近
The tiger we were stalking walked on paper feet
- 那漫长的黑夜  - 它用火焰染红黎明的天际
- And in the endless night  - And in the clear white heat of dawn
把政权夺取
Was gone
- 听！它在悄悄的靠近  - 胜利！
- On silent feet it came  - Victory
- 它有着烈焰的吐息  - 胜利！
- Breathing a sheet of flame  - Victory
- 它带来猎杀的血腥  - 胜利！
- Closing in on its rightful prey  - Victory
- 它的火焰要燃烧一个世纪  - 属于红色巨龙的黎明！
- Burning a hundred years away  - The morning of the dragon
- 属于红色巨龙的黎明！ - 同志们好啊！
- The morning of the dragon  - Brother greeted brother
它如猛虎悄悄的接近
The tiger we were stalking walked on paper feet
- 那漫长的黑夜  - 它用火焰染红黎明的天际
- And in the endless night  - And in the clear white heat of dawn
把政权夺取
Was gone
收容教育三年好滋味
Three years of school was nice
在稻田里种地，汗流浃背
In rice fields, planting rice
你们好厉害啊！
You did good work, you see
劳动改造，重新做人
Re-educating me
靠谎言存在的，不改造就灭亡！
Who lives a lie must change or die
收容教育整三年，江山变色！
Three years, how quick they moved
世界在我眼前变了模样！
Look how the world's improved
西贡！罪恶之都！
Saigon, that queen of sin
现在她叫胡！志！明！
Renamed for Ho Chi Ming
靠谎言存在的，不改造就灭亡！
Who lives a lie must change or die
但是，人，终归是人
But men will always be men
他们觉得给我洗脑成功
They washed out my brain
可我还是我
I'm still what I am
我还是知道我能干什么
Deep inside, I know what I know
也知道我该去哪儿
Wherever I go
我现在嘴上喊“胡大爷”
I speak Uncle Ho
可心里还有“山姆大叔”
And think Uncle Sam
- 你叫陈万代？ - 听您吩咐！
- Your name is Tran Van Dinah?  - At your service
- 以前他们都叫你“工程师”？ - 是的长官！
- You're called the Engineer  - Yes, sir
- 我们的政委同志  - 我刑满了吗？
- The People's Commissar  - Am I free?
把你押送过来的
Has ordered you back here
靠谎言存在的，不改造就灭亡！
Who lives a lie must change or die
我们找到了你想要的这个人
We found the man that you wanted so bad
政委同志，您完全正确
And, Commissar, you were perfectly right
他正要被遣送的北边的劳改营
He had been taken up north to a camp
我们连夜把他解送回来
We brought him down under cover of night
他是亲美分子
Once he had served the American clique
靠出卖我们的姐妹发财
Selling our sisters and daughters for gold
不到一周我们就找到了他
Notice we caught him in less than a week
下命令吧！怎么处置他！
When we get orders, we do what we're told
好了，好了，就这样，可以了
All right, all right, that's it, that's all
你们干的不错，很好
You've done your job, that's it
你们走吧，我来审问他
You go back, I'll take over now
小金
Kim.
替我找到她
You will find her for me
好好给我想想
Crawl from under your shell
你知道她的朋友在哪
You know who her friends were
去，问问她们都知道什么！
Go! See what they can tell
挖地三尺把她找回来！
Sniff her out
否则
Or I swear
我会把你送进鬼门关
You'll look forward to hell
我再也没有见过她
I never saw her again
我已经被你们劳动改造了
I am a different man
我现在已经是社会主义新人了
I've been enlightened since then
实话啊……
Yes
啊，但是，帮个忙还是可以的嘛
But men must help other men
你放心吧，我一定全力寻找
And seeing it's you,I'll work to the bone
我给你四十八小时
I'll give you 48 hours
如果你还想活命，就把她给我带回来
If you want to stay free,don't come back here alone
- 听！它在悄悄的靠近  - 胜利！
- On silent feet it came  - Victory
- 它有着烈焰吐息  - 胜利！
- Breathing a sheet of flame  - Victory
- 它已准备好猎杀的血腥  - 胜利！
- Closing in on its rightful prey  - Victory
它的火焰要燃烧一个世纪
Burning a hundred years away
红色巨龙苏醒了！它散播着宇宙真理
The morning of the dragon,truth lit up the street
它如猛虎悄悄的接近
The tiger we were stalking walked on paper feet
它用火焰染红黎明的天际
And in the clear white heat of dawn
我们已经胜利
Was gone
昨晚我梦见你抱住了我
Last night I dreamed you held me
我们偎依在一起进入梦乡
We slept here side by side
你在我耳边低语
You whispered softly to me
轻声呼唤我的名字
I heard you speak my name
我哭了
I cried
纵然已经过去了好多年
Though I know it's been so many years
可我还是流下了泪滴
Through the silence of my secret tears
你还在我心中
You are here still
我依然
I still
依然相信
I still believe
你会回来
You will return
你会
I know you will
我的心依然为你而坚定
My heart forevermore holds still
依然坚定
Yet still
我依然相信
I still believe
永不心灰意冷的相信
I know as long as I can keep believing
我会活下去
I'll live
真爱永生不熄
Love cannot die
你会回来
You will return
只有我如此坚信
And I alone know why
昨夜我拥你入眠
Last night I held you sleeping
再一次受到噩梦侵袭
Again, the nightmare came
我听见你在喊着什么
I heard you cry out something
听起来好像个人名
A word that sounded like a name
我突然感到了重重的一击
And it hurts me more than I can bear
至今有些事我不能向你提及
Knowing part of you, I'll never share
永远不提
Never know
但我依然
But still
依然相信
I still believe
终有一天我们信心坚定
The time will come
我再把你心扉开启
When nothing keeps us apart
我的心永远为你坚定
My heart forevermore holds still
- 小金！ - 没事了，没事了，我在这儿
- Kim!  - It's all over, I'm here
不要害怕
There is nothing to fear
克里斯，是什么让你如此恐惧？
Chris, what's haunting you?
跟我说说吧，没什么好怕的
Won't you let me inside? There is nothing to hide
是什么在噬咬着你？
What's hurting you?
- 我依然  - 我会一直抱着你
- For still  - I will hold you all night
你什么都不用担心
I will make it all right
- 我依然相信  - 我会守护你的安全
- I still believe  - You are safe with me
- 永远  - 我期待着你的倾诉
- As long  - And I wish you could share
- 永远  - 你隐藏了什么心事
- As I  - What you're hiding in there
- 永远不心灰意冷的相信  - 你承受了什么难言之隐
- Can keep believing, I'll live  - What your hell must be
- 等你回来，我会活下去  - 睡吧睡吧
- I'll live, you will return  - You can sleep now
- 你可以放声哭泣  - 我知道是什么原因
- You can cry now  - And I know why
- 我是你守伴一生的妻啊！ - 我是你的
- I'm your wife now for life  - I'm yours
生死相依！
Until we die
她叫小金，你见过她吗？
Kim? Have you seen this girl?
嘿，你
Hey, you
小宝贝儿！你还认得我吗！
Coo-coo, princess, look who's here
- 我是鬼门关里逃出来的工程师啊！ - 你怎么找到我的？
- Your resurrected Engineer  - How did you find me?
别一惊一乍，我就是顺藤摸瓜
Don't look surprised, I tracked you down
因为我的鼻子最灵啦！
I have the sharpest nose in town
我来是为了拉你一把
I'm here to throw a rope before you drown
因为，人，毕竟是人
For men will always be men
当官的虽然换了，可心思还是那么花
You change the regime, the lust doesn't stop
咱俩再度联手
You and I will team up again
联手从他们身上揩油
Together we'll reap the cream of the crop
工程师，我不想再见到你
Engineer, I don't want you here
你必须明白，我不能再做那种事了
I gave up that life, you must understand
我们出去！我们可以再狠捞一笔！
Just out there is a big shot who waits like a pup
吃香的喝辣的啊！小金！
To come up and eat out of your hand, Kim
荣华富贵又回来了
The good times are back
别说了，太晚了
Don't go on, it's too late
有你在就不晚！
Not too late for my star
- 求求你让我走吧  - 那我就得来硬的了
- Please let me hide in peace  - Better to screw the police
进来吧，政委先生
Come in, Monsieur Commissar
我离开了整三年
Three years I've been away
我们依然还相见
I kept faith we would meet
瞧见了吧？我找到她了
See? I found her for you
你外边站着去！
You, out in the street
出去！都出去！
Out! Get out
冥冥之中的安排
I knew in time, fate would weave a design
你和我终将生活在一起
Tying your life and mine into one
每天我翘首以盼
Each day I'd wait
就像一个战士
Like a soldier must wait
在漫长的黑夜中
Trusting victory to come with the sun
把黎明的胜利期待
After the fight in the still of the night
我的新娘啊！你将珠光宝气
I would picture my bride, bright as jade
我的新人啊！你的人生将大不一样
You'll be my wife, we will build a new life
完成你我父辈的诺言
And fulfill the vow our fathers made
父辈的诺言，不应如此实现
My father's vow can't be honored this way
我在内心的会祈求他的谅解
And I pray in my heart he'll forgive
你对我的要求，我不能答应
What you want now are some words I can't say
如果不在乎谎言，我大可委曲求全
If I lied to you, how could I live?
一个字都别再说了
Don't say any more, not a word
你不能这样，你得学会
You will change, you will learn
看着我
Look at me
给你时间考虑
Don't decide too soon
在我灵魂的深处
Somewhere deep in my soul
没有狂风的吹拂
Shines the smallest of lights
虽然希望的火苗微弱
And no wind blows it out
但是坚定而从容
It burns steady and strong
穿透漆黑的暗夜
Through the darkest of nights
Dju vui vay
yu doi my
vao nyay moy
我许下了爱的誓言
I made a promise once with these words
无论天涯海角永不改变
Which neither time nor distance can change
他一定会回来找我
He will come to me still
你别傻了！你那个美国瘪三跑去过好日子了！
You must be mad, your American Jack has gone for good
他不会回来了
And he'll never come back
- 他跑了，小金！他把你丢下不管了！ - 不会！
- He ran away, Kim, he left you to rot  - No
我敢肯定他现在把你忘干净了
I'm sure by now he already forgot
小金你别傻了，心肝儿，你就别执迷不悟了
Kim, come on now, princess, get off of your cloud
实在抱歉啊长官，她太大声了
I'm sorry, sir, she was talking so loud
政委可是个很了不起的大官儿！
The Commissar is a powerful man
姑娘们都挤破脑袋要嫁给他们！
A girl with brains makes a life where she can
心肝儿，看看你现在
Princess, remember your place
可别让他丢了颜面！
Don't make people lose face
你为什么不看我？
Why do you look away?
我能结束你的痛苦不堪
I can end all this shame
你只要答应
All you need to say is "yes"
小金！
Kim
- 听！它在悄悄的靠近  - 你听见外面那些当兵的了吗？
- On silent feet we came  - You hear those soldiers outside?
- 它有着烈焰吐息  - 他们都听从我的命令
- Breathing a sheet of flame  - They'll do whatever I say
它已准备好猎杀的血腥
Closing in on its rightful prey
我不会改变我的心意！
I cannot change what I feel
- 它的火焰要燃烧一个世纪  - 卫兵！进来！
- Burning a hundred years away  - Soldiers, come!
我让你在我眼前顺从我！
I think you will change before my eyes
我抓到了一个敌人溃败时
This Me-My has just been found
潜伏下来的奸细
She hid the day we closed the bars
看看她还知道什么
Show them that we don't forget
想毫发无损的背叛我们是不可能的
No one betrays us without scars
- 你是个无耻的女人！ - 你是敌人留下的余孽！
- You are a woman who lived without shame  - You're an infection left over from war
- 你玷污了国家的名声！ - 劳动改造或许能收拾你！
- You have dishonored the national name  - Re-education will cure the disease
- 拿你开刀，看看怎么惩治国家的蛀虫！ - 看我怎么收拾这个美国人的婊子！
- You must be shown what we do to a leech  - See how we teach an American's whore
我已经听够了惨叫
I have heard hundreds of speeches like these
求你们了，我再也不想听到惨叫了！
Take it from me, you don't want to hear more
动手吧！同志们！
It's time to act, my friends
现在！
It's time
她无耻至极！
Her face betrays her crime
她要付出代价！
She must pay
她的同党也一样！
And her partner too
住手！
Stop!
出去！
Get out!
我说，你们都出去！
I said, get out!
你就眼睁睁的看着他们宰了我吗？
Are you waiting for them to kill me?
你就不能照他说的做？
Did you not get what he said?
你脑子一定是已经坏掉
There's a big screw loose inside you
我来给你瞧瞧
I will rip it out of your head
那个家伙已经是一条疯狗
There's a mad dog on a rampage
- 姑且顺服，大家都能满足！ - 不行！
- Just appease him, everyone wins  - No
我才不管你跟他会怎样！你就给我答应，咱们还能留条小命！
I don't give a shit if you love him, say you do, and we leave with our skins
我有我爱的丈夫！
I have a husband I love
他并不虚无！
Real as the sun in the sky
- 我不能靠谎言苟活  - 你这傻瓜！
- I cannot live with a lie  - You stupid...
你不知道胳膊拧不过大腿吗？
Do you see now who has power?
你不要心存幻想
Do you still think crazy things?
克里斯会从天而降
Chris will come to me like the phoenix
他会张开双臂带我走！
And he'll take me off on his wings
你这是背叛国家！
You're a traitor to your country
如果这是叛国，那你就动手吧！
If I am, then let it be
现在是你生死的抉择！
I am talking of life or death now
我宁死也不跟你！
I am talking of staying free
好吧，我也没办法了，我滚出去了
So there it is now,I'll be moving on
如果你不需要我，我现在就消失
If you don't need me, I'd rather be gone
孤男寡女并不需要别人在场
Two kids in love don't need strangers around
- 你赶紧给我滚！ - 胡大爷万岁！我鸟悄的
- You, just get out!  - Ho Chi Ming, I won't make a sound
现在，就咱俩了
And as for you
- 跟我走吧  - 绝不！
- Come with me  - No!
我有个秘密
There is a secret
你并不知道
That you don't know
我有种力量
There is a force here
我从未显露
I never show
你说我背叛了
You say it's treason
我爹的诺言
To keep my vow
可一年又一年
Season after season
我依然苟活
I've survived somehow
如果你想知道
If you want the reason
就给我仔细观瞧！
I will show you now
小天！
Tam!
没事的
It's OK.
看看，苏一，这就是我的孩子
Look, Thu, this is my son
他就是我的一切
He is all that I have
现在你知道我为什么一定要拒绝
Now you see why I must tell you "no"
别人没有必要看到你的这个孽种！
No one must ever see this thing you're showing me
你这混蛋毁了我的名声！
Your bastard fouls our name
无论我怎样，孩子是无辜的！
My baby's not to blame for what I've done
你现在必须选择你的立场！
You must decide upon which side you're really on
- 你这领着孽种的娼妇！ - 不要那样说我！
- You whores to have that kid  - No! That isn't what I did
别碰我的孩子！
Don't touch my son
你看这样行不行？
You must see how it is
就姑且嫁给我
When you're my wife
这孩子留着，就说是咱俩的
Keeping this child of his brands us for life
要是不这样，这孩子也就别活了？
No alternative, this child cannot live
不！
No!
我绝不会让你碰他
You will not touch him
- 别碰我的孩子  - 小金！
- Don't touch my boy  - Kim
他是我活下去的希望
He's what I live for
我生命唯一的动力
He's my only joy
- 我绝不让你碰他！ - 他是阶级敌人！
- You will not touch him  - He is my enemy
就是他让你如此死心塌地！
It's he who turns you from me
- 别碰我的孩子！ - 我要把他抹去！
- Don't touch my boy  - Erase him from your life
忘掉他！
Even your memory
- 他是我活下去的希望  - 他只是你不该有的记忆！
- He's what I live for  - He's one drop in a flood
跟我走，给我生孩子！
Left here to taint our blood
- 他是我生命唯一的动力  - 我们的名分，是父辈的预定！
- He's my only joy  - Our marriage bond is sworn
忘掉这个孽种！
Forget that he was born
退后！
Get back!
你敢拿枪指着我？
Of course you have a gun
- 我绝不会让你碰我的孩子！ - 我可是你的叔伯兄弟！
- You will not touch my little boy  - And now you'll shoot your cousin
而且还是美国枪！
And it's a US gun
- 不要逼我！ - 美国已经完了！
- And do not test my will  - A gun that lost the war
你是反动顽固分子！
You're the corrupted one
- 我警告你！ - 来啊，开枪啊！别犹豫啊！
- I'm warning you  - Go on and shoot, don't wait
- 为了他我会扣动扳机！ - 就为了保护他这个孽种！
- For him I'll kill  - To save your bastard son
开枪！别犹豫！
You must not hesitate
我现在天旋地转
The earth moves where I stand
- 子弹推上了枪口  - 开枪啊！
- I feel the turning of a wheel  - Shoot
- 我手上只有这支枪！ - 开枪啊！
- I feel nothing in my hand  - Shoot
- 这支冰冷的枪！ - 开枪啊！
- Not even the chill of steel  - Shoot
我绝不会让你带走他！
You will not take my child
你根本就没杀过人！
You don't know how to kill
我别无选择
I have no other choice
我必须开枪！住手！
What I must do I will! No!
这是光荣的时刻啊！
This is the hour
我们伟大的祖国！
This is our land
我们伟大的力量！
We found the power
就在同志们手上！
In our brother's hand
暴风雨中！
And from a storm
- 不！ - 灯火闪耀
- No!  - Pierced with light
闪电撕开乌云
Fierce and white the lightning came
光芒把黑暗照亮
A brightening flame to end the night
领袖在鼓舞着我们！
One man to heed us
无论你是男是女
Each girl, each boy
一个声音指引着我
One voice to lead us
伟大的战歌
In a song OTIOSE
这是庄严的时刻
This is the hour
这是我们伟大的祖国！
This is our land
如果你不想死于非命，那就看我怎么做
If you want to die in bed, follow my example
乌云来了你得戴草帽啊
When you see a cloud ahead,it's time to show your class
当兵的来了赶紧猫下腰
Hit the door before they make a target of your ass
兵荒马乱命难活
If you want to die in bed in times of revolution
心中要有伟大的党啊，当你看到红旗飘！
When the flag they fly is red, let pride fill up your chest
抓住机会不要放啊！快往西边逃！
Meanwhile pack a sack and take the first boat heading west
哪去了？哪去了？
Where's it? Where's it?
啊，找到了
It's still here!
幸亏在舒坦的时候留了一手
My precious souvenirs of all the golden years
镀金的劳力士手表，挺像真的，啊？
Rolex watches in steel that look practically real
要想去曼谷东山再起，我得要点资金
I'll need a little stock to start me in Bangkok
如果你不想死于非命，就别管天打雷劈
If you want to die in bed, forgot about your karma
当你命悬一线，就别怨天怨地
When your life hangs by a thread, don't cry about the fates
拿上一沓钞票，赶紧去美国溜之大吉！
Grab a stash of cash and buy a strip joint in the States
等一下，这是我的珍藏
Let me stop for a bit, this was my greatest hit
西贡小姐的皇冠，谁得到它，谁就是城里的半边天
Miss Saigon in her crown, I made queen of the town
我拿它赚钱，姑娘们换了一遍又一遍
I got them paying more for just another whore
我来了，美国
Here I come, USA
你的宠儿正在路上
Your next champ's on his way
因为人总要活出个人样！
For men will always be men
到哪儿都一样
The rules are the same
不管皇帝还是草民
For kings or for clerks
美元、法郎、日元，什么都行
Give me francs or dollars or yen
我就能重新开张
I'll set up a game
我知道该怎么干
I know how things work
脑瓜灵活的我为什么
Why was I born of a race
诞生在这个土里刨食的国家？
That thinks only of rice and hates entrepreneurs?
我！属于真正属于我的地方
Me, I belong in a place where a man sets his price
你付钱，我就卖命
And you pay and he's yours
我应该是，美！国！人！
I should be American
生活在，那应许的土地！
Where every promise lands
每一个生意人都知道该去哪！
And every businessman knows where he stands
第一站，曼谷；第二站，罗马
First stop Bangkok, then I roam
然后漂洋过海
'Cross that ocean white with foam
来到我心中真正的家园！
To the place that's my heart's true home
美国啊！！
America
美国啊~~~~~
如果你不想成为孤魂野鬼
If you want to die in bed en route to your Nirvana
你就必须牢牢抓住机会
You grab your chance and plunge ahead
去人人都能活命的地方
And go where people win
天堂就在那里！
Heaven's there
但是，他妈的……
But shit...
你需要绿卡才能进去！
You need a visa to get in
噢！
Ah!
给我出去
Get out!
工程师，苏一死了
Engineer, Thu is dead
他想杀了我的儿子，我把他打死了
He was going to kill my baby and I shot
你说啥？那是谁？
You did what? Who is that?
你被盯上了，赶紧带他离开，再见！
You'll be followed, get him out of here, goodbye
- 他妈的！ - 我和小天必须离开
- Fuck!  - We must leave, Tam and I
我们今晚必须去美国
We must set off for America tonight
好，完美的计划
All right, just like that
但是这怎么实现呢？
Tell me how and while you're at it, tell me why
我梦见了我的丈夫
I hear the voice of my soldier
他说他要见他的孩子
Telling me to bring his son
你说什么？这个混血儿是美国大兵的？
You're telling me this half-breed brat is born the son of a Marine?
让我看看他有没有美国大鼻子
Let me see his Western nose
这孩子长得太好看了！
This bastard is the most beautiful sight I've ever seen
我有美国护照了
A passport in my hand
我的新生活开始了
My new life can begin
你这美国少爷
Your brat's American
他们一定会让我移民
So they must let us in
在人间的乐园欢笑
In the playground of mankind
实现我多年的幻想
The movie in my mind
从现在开始，就说我是你的大哥
I'm your dear brother from now on
我们的家人都没了
And all our family is gone
孩砸！快亲亲你的陈叔叔
Boy, kiss your brand-new Uncle Tran
这孩子真听话
This kid is OK
他就是我们通往
He is our entree
美国的通行证
To the USA
我只要把他俩紧紧抓在手里
With these two little diamonds to bait my hooks
我就能登上“豪华游轮人民号”
I'll book us on a cruise: "Boat people deluxe"
我以后就再也不害怕湄公河里的野兽了
Don't worry about sharks out in the Mekong Bay
毕竟找蛇头的风险太高了
The pirates taking us are more scary any day
你待在这里藏好，千万别露面
You just stay here and hide, don't show your face outside
照看好这个小宝贝儿，我出去，“设计”一下
Take care of our little dear, I will go engineer
如果你不想死于非命
If you want to die in bed
就别想什么“民族大义”
Don't care too much for country
赶紧逃到海上
Hit the open sea instead
溜之大吉
And float there like a cork
为什么不呢？
Yeah, why not?
胡大爷！
Uncle Ho
胡…胡…胡…胡…胡…胡
Oh-ho ho-ho-ho...
胡大爷我就要去纽约啦！
I'll have to call you from New York
纽约~~哦~~！
New York
约哦~~！约哦~~！约哦~~！约哦~~！
我的臂弯就是你的摇篮
You who I cradled in my arms
你从来不要求我什么
You asking as little as you can
真像个小大人儿
Little snip of a little man
我命中注定要做你的妈妈
I know I'd give my life for you
你突然就来到这个世上
You didn't ask me to be born
你
You
你为何要承受痛苦和挣扎
Why should you learn of war or pain?
我本应保护你免受苦难
To make sure you're not hurt again
我发誓我要用生命保护你
I swear I'd give my life for you
爱能摒除一切恐惧
I've tasted love beyond all fear
在那美好的夜晚，是爱把你带到了我身边
And you should know it's love that brought you here
And in one perfect night
那夜繁星璀璨
When the stars burned like new
我做了我该做的事
I knew what I must do
我给了你无限可能的人生
I'll give you a million things I'll never own
我带给了一个你将拥有的世界
I'll give you a world to conquer when you're grown
你将选择人生的模样
You will be who you want to be
你可以向命运索要赐予
You can choose whatever heaven grants
只要你能勇敢地活下去
As long as you can have your chance
我发誓我要用生命保护你
I swear I'll give my life for you
每当夜晚惊醒，我就会想他
Some nights I wake up reaching for him
他仿佛在床头偷偷的看我
I feel his shadow brush my head
醒来发现那只是斑斑的月光
But it's just moonlight on my bed
他是真实的？他是虚假的？
Was he a ghost? Was he a lie?
他让我如此欢欣又如此忧伤
That made my body laugh and cry
当我彷徨，只有我们的骨血睡在我身旁
Then by my side, the proof I see, his little one
太阳上的神明啊！
Gods of the sun
把他带给我吧！
Bring him to me
你将选择人生的模样
You will be who you want to be
你可以向命运索要赐予
You can choose whatever heaven grants
只要你能勇敢地活下去
As long as you can have your chance
我发誓我要用生命保护你
I swear I'd give my life for you
没人能阻止我要做的事
No one can stop what I must do
我发誓
I swear
我要用生命守护你
I'd give my life for you
没有土地！没有家园！
No place, no home
没有生命！没有希望！
No life, no hope
没有可能！没有可能！
No chance, no change
- 不能反悔！不能回头！ - 没有土地！没有家园！
- No regret, no return  - No place, no home
- 不能反悔！不能回头！ - 没有生命！没有希望！
- No regret, no return  - No life, no hope
- 不能反悔！不能回头！ - 没有可能！没有可能！
- No regret, no return  - No chance, no change
每一天！每一夜！
One day, one night
终有一天！
One day
他们是战争的遗孤
They're called Boi Doi
卑微有如尘土
The dust of life
在战场上孕育，在战乱中降生
Conceived in hell and born in strife
他们是活生生的见证
They are the living reminder
是被我们辜负了的见证
Of all the good we failed to do
我们无法忘怀，不能忘怀，他们如同我们自己的孩子
We can't forget, must not forget,that they are all our children too
曾经以为，我在战场上活下来，就不用辜负良心的谴责
Like all survivors, I once thought when I'm home, I won't give a damn
现在我终于知道
But now I know I'm caught
我从未离开过越南
I'll never leave Vietnam
对我们来说战争并没有结束
War isn't over when it ends
有些画面在时常提醒着我
Some pictures never leave your mind
那是孩子们的脸
They are the faces of the children
每一个我们留下的孩子
The ones we left behind
他们都是战争的孤儿
They're called Boi Doi
卑微有如尘土
The dust of life
在战场上孕育，在战乱中降生
Conceived in hell and born in strife
他们是活生生的见证
They are the living reminder
是被我们辜负了的见证
Of all the good we failed to do
我们无法忘怀，不能忘怀，他们如同我们自己的孩子
We can't forget, must not forget, that they are all our children too
他们到处碰壁
These kids hit walls on every side
他们不属于任何地方
They don't belong in any place
他们无法隐瞒
Their secret they can't hide
他们长了一张美国脸
It's printed on their face
我从没想到有一天我会为他们奔走呼号
I never thought one day I'd plead for half-breeds from a land that's torn
我无法忍受难民营中他们向外张望的目光
But then I saw a camp for children whose crime was being born
他们都是战争的孤儿
They're called Bi Di
卑微有如尘土
The dust of life
在战场上孕育，在战乱中降生
Conceived in hell and born in strife
我们欠他们一个父亲和一个家
We owe them fathers and a family
一个他们应得的家
A loving home they never knew
因为在内心的深处
Because we know deep in our hearts
他们也是我们的孩子
That they are all our children too
这是灵魂深处的渴望！
These are souls in need
他们渴望我们给于！
They need us to give
他们渴望机会，活下去
Someone has to pay for their chance to live
- 伸出援手！ - 他们都是战争的孤儿
- Help me try  - They're called Bi Di
卑微有如尘土
The dust of life
在战场上孕育，在战乱中降生
Conceived in hell and born in strife
他们是活生生的见证
They are the living reminder
是被我们辜负了的见证
Of all the good we failed to do
- 所以我们知道  - 所以我们知道
- That's why we know  - That's why we know
- 在我们的心中  - 我们内心的深处
- Deep in our hearts  - That deep down in our hearts
- 所以我们知道  - 他们都是
- That's why we know  - That they are all
我们的孩子
Our children too
- 约翰！ - 克里斯！
- John.  - Chris!
- 还好吗？ - 约翰你太了不起了
- Look at you.  - John, you were great.
我能单独跟你聊聊吗？
Can I see you alone?
现在仔细讲讲电话里的事吧
I've got to know what you meant on the phone
是什么消息？你只能告诉我？
Hey, what is this news you received you could only tell me?
我在曼谷的团队一直在给我传递消息
A lot of groups use my Bangkok staff to process problems on their behalf
这是我在大使馆带来的信息
We got this in from the embassy
我很难开口，你自己看看吧
It's not easy to tell you, it's best that you see
小金，是关于小金的，对吗？
Kim. It's about Kim, isn't it?
只有你知道我是多么难以启齿
Only you know how hard I have tried to get word
先告诉我，不要说别的，她还活着吗？
Tell me first, nothing else, tell me did she survive?
你应该先看看，不过别担心，她，还活着
You should read the report, Chris, but yes, she's alive
你不明白，约翰！你不明白！
You don't know, John, these nightmares
在夜里，我们见
The things that I've seen
我看到她葬身火海，看到她倒在我的枪下
I-I've seen her face burned, seen her shot with my gun
我穿过了一条又一条的街道，听到的只有尖叫！
I've chased her through streets and heard nothing but screams
怎么了？还有什么？说啊？
What's wrong? Come on, there is still something more
她有了个孩子
She has a child
是你的
You have a son
你也许不信，但是我已经梦到
You won't believe me, but I dreamed this, John
在梦里的西贡，我还真的梦到了他
He's in the nightmare when I see Saigon
- 天哪，约翰，我已经结婚了  - 我知道
- Jesus, John, I am married  - I know
这是真的吗？
Is this story for real?
虽然这只是一条消息
I'm only telling you what I received
但我的消息一般都很准确
But our reports can usually be believed
小金现在曼谷的酒吧里
Kim's a bar girl in Bangkok
兄弟我知道你现在的感受
Pal, I know how you feel
这消息太迟了，我的人生已经重新开始了
It's too late! I have a whole new life
我有个我爱的妻子，她不能可有可无
I have a wife I love, she can't just disappear
听我说，克里斯，我知道你很震惊
Listen, Chris, I know the shock you've had
也不一定是坏事，你看这样行不行？
It isn't always bad, there are solutions here
约翰啊，我从来没跟她讲过
John, I never told her
我的妻子，我怎么跟他说？
My wife, how can I tell her?
有个孩子，怎么办？
A child, what can I do?
哦，老天，小金啊！
Oh, Jesus, Kim
我能怎么办？
What can I do?
以前也有过这种事
I have learned the best thing for a couple to do
但我怎么和她开口？
How can I tell her?
你俩一起去曼谷
You should both go to Bangkok
- 我又必须告诉她  - 没错，艾伦也去
- I have to tell her  - I mean Ellen too
我俩？
Us both?
你俩都应该去
You both should go
嘿！小伙子们，来啊？
Hey, guys, come on
但是首先，首先，艾伦要先知道
But first... First Ellen has to know
怎么了？
What?
- 你还好吗？ - 不好
- Are you OK?  - No.
- 我们得谈谈  - 好的
- We need to talk.  - Sure.
过来吧，完蛋了……
Come on. Fuck.
- 曼谷最漂亮的姑娘！ - 盘儿靓条儿顺啊！
- Best girls in Bangkok  - Pussy galore!
- 注意啦！ - 嘿！你在那边干什么呢？
- Check it out!  - Hey, what are you doing there?
- 天天就知道游手好闲！ - 我会回去工作的，老板
- You're nothing but second-rate...  - I'll get back to work, boss.
这婊子养的老板。嘿！找姑娘吗？要啥样的？
Son of a bitch. Hey, you looking for a girl? What can I get you?
大胸妹儿？嘿！老主顾！
You want a big-breasted girl? Hey, you're back!
我说过了，那姑娘干净极了
I told you that girl was clean.
这次想玩儿点什么？男人婆吗？
What can I get you this time A girl that looks like a boy?
还是换个人妖？还是这个跳舞的？
A boy who looks like a girl? Or someone who looks like this?
多漂亮啊！
Yeah!
- 姑娘们！ - 来吧台这边
- Girls  - Come to my bar.
- 我手上有姑娘  - 待会儿再谢我
- I got girls  - You'll thank me later.
- 动人的姑娘  - 幸亏没带老婆来
- Gorgeous girls  - I'm glad my wife's not here with me
来，看看这个，看看这个姑娘，看她怎么样？
Check this out. Look at this girl. The way she moves.
绝对能……你干嘛去？
It's impossible. You...
浪费口舌
What a waste
为了生存，我只能服服帖帖
To pay for my keep, I'm rounding up sheep
为了在曼谷攒够钱
To fleece here in Bangkok
我只能作践自己
I'm disgraced
我抓不住要领
I can't get ahead
因为曼谷对我来说毫不刺激
There's nothing as dead as peace here in Bangkok
十美分一小时，他们出的也太少了
Ten cents an hour, that's the most they pay
照这样，我只能游到美国
I'll have to swim to the USA
姑娘大减价！买一送一
Special offer on pussies, buy one, get one free
如果你想找点乐子，满足原始的欲望！
If you're looking for fun, original sin
如果你觉得别处没趣，那你看看这里！
If you want to put out, then you've gotta come in
- 姑娘们！ - 嘿！小伙子
- Girls  - Hey, boys
- 别像个熊包一样  - 给我来个姑娘！
- Don't stand around like wimps  - I got girls
留神，那帮人是拉皮条的
Watch out, those guys, they're really pimps
- 漂亮！ - 你想来点刺激的？
- Pearls  - You want some thrills?
- 那就别犹豫  - 半价！
- Come on and grab it  - Half the price
俩姑娘，一边一个
Two girls, a gerbil and a rabbit
- 你够下流的，你喜欢那样？ - 嘿，过来
- Nasty stuff, you like that  - Hey, come to me
- 你看到了什么？ - 乒乓球！哈！
- Look what you'll see  - Ping pong, ha
嘿，开个玩笑
Hey, that's a joke
顺便看看我吐烟圈的绝技
Mine blows smoke for a small extra fee
嘿，老弟，来我这感受一下
Hey, Joe, try taking a little excursion
玩点不一样的你会更刺激
You'll all feel good from a little perversion
- 哦，是吗？ - 先泡个澡，再来个马杀鸡
- Oh, yeah?  - Massage requiring total immersion
- 哦，对啊！ - 有些特别的地方
- Oh, wow!  - Some strange positions
- 比如波斯  - 哦，不！
- They say are Persian  - Oh, no!
- 我可是摩门教徒！（译者注：早起摩门教可以一夫多妻）  - 酒水我买单
- I am a Mormon!  - Drinks are on me
好！宝贝儿！去吧，第一个姑娘免费
Yeah, baby! Go! First girl is free
我还能说什么？这只是小小的营销手段！
Hey, what can I say? You get me for a small extra fee
对不起我摸错了！
It was only a joke.
你想要姑娘吗，先生？看看这个如何？
You want a girl, sir? You'll like one of these
小金在这儿？我能见见她吗？
You have a Kim here? Can I see her, please?
你先照看一下
You pick 'em well.
约翰先生，是你吗？
Monsieur John. Is that you?
“工程师”？上帝啊，你也在？
The Engineer? Jesus Christ, you're here too?
哦，老伙计！
Oh, you
在所有朋友里面，你是我最想念的那个！
Of all my friends, you're the one that I miss
- 我在找小金  - 你爱死你了！
- I'm looking for Kim  - I love you so
还有那个叫克里斯的家伙
You and your buddy Chris
我就是为他来的，小金的孩子
I'm here about him; Kim has a child
- 生于  - 一九七五年
- Born in  - '75
我替你填好了
I filled that out, and it's you who arrive
你现在离成功近在咫尺了
You'll find the end of your quest here in our little dive
伙计你太了不起了
Man, I'm impressed
美国人的办事效率真高啊
American clerks, a system that works
- 高的真是没谁了  - 听着，没时间胡扯
- There's really no other  - Listen, spare me the gas
她真的有孩子吗？
ls there really a child?
哦，没错！我们得救了！
Oh, yes, we're blessed
小金现在有泰国身份了
And Kim's on a trip for citizenship
我现在是她大哥
And I am her brother
你是她哪门子大哥？
You're her brother, my ass
来吧，带我进去
Come on, take me inside
瞧瞧啊，小金，谁来了？
Look, Kim, who got our application
我说过了，跟着我混准没错
I said I'd bring us all salvation
哦天哪！约翰先生，一定是克里斯派你来的？
Oh, my God, Monsieur John, yes, of course he sent you
这儿不方便，这附近有能谈话的地方吗？
Not in here, is there someplace near we could talk?
把你的手拿开，她下班了，去再找一个
Take your hands off, she's finished, go find someone else
跟我来，我有很多话，先听我说
Come with me, there's a lot I've got to say first
克里斯来了吗？他来了吗？
Chris is here, say he's here
哦，上帝啊，这是真的
Oh, my God, it's all true
我建议，交给我来处理
I suggest whatever may be, you leave this to me
你照看好孩子
Just play little mother
- 我必须搞清楚  - 我都知道
- What I need to find out  - Anything
让她单独跟我说
She can tell me alone
你带我去找克里斯，现在我能就离开
Can you take me to Chris? I can leave here right now
- 是我们！ - 我们在这里待了好久
- We  - We've been here for so long
- 我只能靠这个谋生  - 在海上飘了一个月啊！
- I took this job to survive  - One month at sea
我们几乎就要葬身海底
I was sure we'd drown
但是一想到克里斯，他就给我力量活下去
But I thought about Chris and we didn't go down
虽然为了生存不得不卖笑，但是我们等到你来了
I've done terrible things, but we're safe and you're here
也许我的祈求终于得到了回应
So perhaps all the gods have begun to forgive
那位先生点了香槟吗？
Has the gentleman ordered champagne?
她给那位先生点的
She was about to get it
你要么赶紧回去干活，要么就滚！
You'd better get back on the chain, or get out
- 约翰先生  - 我真受不了这个老板了
- Monsieur John  - I am sick of that prick
- 快点，在他发觉之前  - 跟我来
- Quick, before he gets wise  - Look at this
去带他看看孩子，看看他的眼睑
Let John look at our kid, see the lids of his eyes?
- 过来，孩子  - 让约翰见见
- Come see, love  - Let John have his surprise
- 我们去找你爹爹  - 再来一瓶！
- Come see Chris  - Open a bottle!
看啊，山姆大叔，嘿！
Look, Uncle Sam, hey?
我就要成功了
How nice I am
我这么做完全是为了她的孩子
I'm doing all this just for Tam
一个美国小子！
An American boy
你看，约翰，这就是他的儿子
Look, John, this is his son
- 来！击个掌！ - 看他俩笑起来是不是一样？
- Give me five.  - Don't they have the same smile?
他等他父亲的消息，已经很久很久了
He's been waiting for his father for a long, long while
我这次来是公干
I'm not here as a friend
不是私人往来
I have a job to do
我现在为了孤儿们奔波，才来到了这里
It's strange to find my work should lead me here to you
我把你的情况都告诉了克里斯
Chris knows all about you, I have shown him all this
现在你该来了解一下克里斯的情况了
But I think that it's time you know all about Chris
好啊，都告诉我吧，我等不及了
Yes, tell me everything, I beg you
经过漫长的等待
How I've longed for this to start
这些东西太多了
All my prayers are finally answered
我怎么能看得完
This is too much for one heart
小金，他失去你的时候几乎都疯了
Kim, he went crazy when he lost you
一整年都不开口说话
Spoke to no one for a year
他说的第一句话就是，“我终于到家了”
Then he finally said, "I'm home now"
“我的人生要重新开始”
"My life has to go on here"
- 你在说什么？ - 小金啊
- What are you talking about?  - Kim
请你先让我说完
Let me finish talking, please
那是在三年前
That was three whole years ago
是的是的，我知道
Yes, yes, I know
孤单一个人的守候
I know how pain can grow
两地分离的痛苦，越发与日俱增
When the rock you hold on to is a love miles away
听我说
Listen, please
我知道你要说什么
I already know the story
带我们去美国吧，约翰
Take us to the USA, John
等我们都搞清楚了，你会见到他的
When we're finished here, you'll see him
克里斯是和我一起来的
Chris arrived with me today
哦，小天，他来了！
Oh, Tam, he's here
他来了，他如此接近
He's here, he's so near
我们今天呼吸着同样的空气
We might breathe the same air tonight
你的父亲来了
Your father's here
- 我是如此的艰难  - 这让我怎么开口？
- I dreamed so hard  - I can't tell her like this
- 我坚守着这份信念  - 我这样岂不是做了坏事？
- I kept my faith  - I should not be the one
- 现在如此的真切  - 克里斯必须先见到他的孩子
- And now it's true  - Chris must first see his son
- 现在我能感到  - 他们在档案上可没说
- Now I can see  - They don't say in the files
- 我们终于等到了结局  - 她还如此坚定
- We've been watched over  - There's a woman in love
- 我们重获了新生  - 她还如此坚定
- And our life's about to start  - Here
- 她坚定的目光  - 太阳与月亮
- What I see in her eyes  - Sun and moon
- 终将在天空团聚  - 克里斯还不知道
- Will be together  - Chris don't know nothing of
忽然要承受的如此之多
This is too much for one heart
现在我只能做一件事
There's only one thing I can do
就是把克里斯带来见你
I must bring Chris here to see you
- 谢谢你  - 好
- Thank you.  - OK.
我想我说过！孩子不能来这里
I thought I said no kids around
那个小羔子在这里干什么？
So what's the brat doing here?
你最好给我小心点，我一直盯着你俩
You better take care, I'm watching both of you
你，和你那个工程师
You and your Engineer
先森，你想按摩吗？
Sir, would you like a massage?
不，谢了，不用了
No, thanks, it's not my scene
我这里有男宠，就在笼子里
I can get boys from La Cage
- 我没兴趣，快让开  - 看路啊！先森！先森！
- Whatever, man. Get out of my way.  - Watch out, sir! Sir!
他怎么走了？
Why is he leaving?
你笑什么？
What is that look?
他马上就要上钩了
He was right on the hook
别告诉我说他已经开溜了
Don't tell me he slipped free
工程师啊，克里斯来了
Engineer, Chris is here
约翰回去把他带来
John is going to get him and bring him to me
我的心都快要跳出来了
My heart's ready to burst
见到他我该先说什么？
I don't know what I'll tell him first
那家伙根本就不值得信任
That guy is no one to trust
否则那个大兵怎么刚知道他有个孩子？
Or a soldier who just learned he fathered a son
你先拖住克里斯
You got to get to Chris first
在他脚底抹油之前，我先知道他住在哪
I will find his address now before he can run
- 蠢货  - 他一定不会失信
- Stupid  - You can trust what he'll do
- 我向你担保，你不用担心  - 你担保？
- Don't you worry, I'll mention you  - You'll mention me?
别给我搞砸了，小婊砸，我不想节外生枝！
Don't screw with me, little bitch, I don't want any hitch
照我说的做！
You just do as you're told
你去他的住处
You go to his hotel
我在背后运作
I'll be working as well
保住我们的摇钱树
Guarding our bag of gold
无论你去哪里，我都跟随你
Tell me where and I'll go
我知道他会一直呵护我
He'll be longing for me, I know
你带我走过电闪雷鸣
You have brought me through the lightning
你一直在远处守望着我
You have watched me from afar
你会了解然后接纳我
You know all and you forgive me
我们会是好夫妻
Loving parents that you are
- 请你  - 你这傻姑娘继续吧
- Please  - Go on, talk to your ghosts
- 给我们未来的生活  - 继续向鬼魂祷告吧，你会失望的
- May your daughter have your blessing  - Little girl, till you're blue
带来祝福
On the life about to start
- 你只有一次机会，就一次  - 我们就要去往新的国度
- You have one chance, just one  - We must journey to a new world
- 他快来了，你要专心  - 我忽然要承受的如此之多
- He's here, talking to you  - This is too much for one heart
我来安排
I'll fix this
你打扮漂亮点
Make yourself pretty.
你以为我走远了吗？
Did you think I'd gone away?
我就是你手下的冤魂
I am the man you killed that day
冰冷的子弹射入了我的胸膛
Cold, with a bullet inside my chest
我的尸体虽然僵硬
My corpse may be sleeping
但是我的鬼魂依然不宁
But my soul won't rest
我是你心中隐藏的罪恶
I'm the crime that you hid
你尽管尝试吧！但你永远也忘不掉你的所作所为！
You can try, but you'll never forget what you did
在我这里你永远不会得到宽恕！
You will never be free
直到你再次来到我的身边！
Not as long as there's me
你以为你会逃过早已预定的命运吗！
Did you think you would escape the judgment that was planned?
你以为你不会遭到报应吗！
Did you think you would escape the truth's avenging hand?
你以为逃出了越南就高枕无忧了吗！
Just because you have escaped the boundaries of your land?
我来了！
I'm here
我来了！我永远不会消失！！
I'm here, I'm never dead!
我来了！我就是你心里最阴暗的秘密！
I'm here, I am the guilt inside your head
你以为那个美国兵跟别人不一样？
You think your Marine's not like other men
他抛弃了你一次
He betrayed you once
还会有第二次！
And he will again
想想那天晚上
Think about that night
他最终回到了哪里！
Where was he back then?
我带你逃出去，快跑！
I'm getting you out! Let's go!
对不起中士，形势恶化了
Sorry, Sergeant, as things degenerate
我给你的是全部的移民手续
All I'm giving her are her emigration papers
不能再等了！
Without the wait
- 在这里签名！ - 真他妈的！
- Sign here  - Bullshit
然后她就能登上我们的航空母舰
This'll get her on board the carrier
你必须确定即使到了美国
You're declaring that you will marry her
她依然是你的合法妻子
When you get back to the States
在这里签名，快点！
Sign here, come on
根据总统的命令
By order of the old man
大使馆马上就关闭了
The embassy will close according to plan
我给你多争取了一对夫妻的移民申请资格
I'll stretch a couple of rules to issue her pass
- 谢谢你！ - 那就对了，你准备好了吗？
- Thank you  - That's it, you're ready
坐稳了！你是下一个！
Nice ass, you're next
根据总统的命令
By order of the old man
我们必须要处理好东南亚移民问题
We're processing the gooks as fast as we can
没错！就是越南！嘿！别让我发狠！
I mean Vietnamese, hey, don't get me wrong
我不可能马上都把你们救走！去那边等着！
Can't save these looks for the Cong, right? Get in there
老天，我跟使馆打好招呼了，别磨蹭了
Christ, I'm due at the embassy, no time to lose
我不想让你离开！
I don't want you to leave me today
至少战争拖延了几天让我们渡过了蜜月
Well, at least Uncle Sam bought our honeymoon cruise
- 如果你要走了，那我也和你一起走！ - 听我说，我把枪给你留下
- If you're going, I don't want to stay  - Look, I'm leaving my gun
- 趁着还有点时间，赶紧收拾！ - 我照你说的做
- We've got time, stay and pack  - I will do whatever you say
在敌人进攻前，我有好多话要对你说
I'll get plenty of word when the CC attack
你在屋里等着，直到我回来
I want you in that bed waiting when I get back
对不起中士！我们不能再拖延了，参谋部让我们赶快撤离！
Sorry, Sergeant, we must accelerate, State Department says we evacuate
命令我们拂晓前离开这里
The word is, we must be out by dawn
对不起中士！这是华盛顿下达的命令
Sorry, Sergeant, it's straight from Washington
现在起不能离开营地
No one leaves the grounds now, not anyone
物资都搬上飞机了，我们要走了！快走！
As fast as we load the planes, we're gone, go!
保持安静，不要喊叫
OK, keep quiet, don't shout
在你们都撤离前，大使先生不会离开
The ambassador won't leave till everyone's out
直升机已经上路了，足够们所有人乘坐
The choppers are on their way have room for you all
他们在爬墙！
They're climbing over the wall
退后！退后！我说过了，不要大喊大叫！
Get back, get back, I tell you, don't shout
在你们都撤离前，大使先生不会离开
The ambassador won't leave till everyone's out
大使命令我们丢下难民！
The ambassador just sent an order to freeze
那就这样吧！越南人不要靠近！我们走！
That's it, no more Vietnamese, get in
锁上大门！
Lock the gates
我是美军士兵的妻子，请让我过去吧！
I'm the wife of a soldier, please let me through
等一等！帮帮我！我要见你们的长官，我该怎么办？
Wait, help me, who must I pay? Tell me what I must do
- 克里斯！ - 让我出去！
- Chris!  - Let me out
- 不行！ - 那是我的新婚妻子！
- No!  - I've got to get back for my bride
不要！听我说！我丈夫正在里面等我！
No, listen, someone, my husband is waiting inside
求你了，小金，接电话啊！
Please, Kim, hear the phone
我出不去了
I can't get there
你赶紧回家
Please be home
再见了，克里斯
Please, Chris
没人发现我被丢在了这里
No one sees I am lost here
来找我吧，求你了
Find me, please
求求你！不管怎样！让我过去！
Please get me through, I don't care how
不要这样把她从我身边带走
Don't take my love away, not now
- 噢！克里斯啊！我被丢下了！ - 你要保重！
- Oh, Chris, I can't get free  - Please get free
- 我依然和你在一起！ - 我永远和你在一起！
- Still I'm with you  - I am with you
等着我！
Wait for me
对不起中士，你必须进入使馆
Sorry, Sergeant, inside the embassy
我们正在突围争取时间
We are pulling out now and there will be no more reprieves
我会赶回来的！
I've got till the old man leaves
克里斯别胡闹了！大使现在就要离开了
Chris, don't be an ass! The ambassador is leaving now
- 带我走吧！ - 带上我的孩子！
- Take me with you  - Take my children
- 我这里有证明！ - 我投靠了中情局
- I have a letter here  - I helped the CIA
他们会把我们都杀光！
They'll kill who they find here
不要丢下我们不管！
Don't leave us behind here
我的妻子已经离开了
I've a wife who left already
我在纽约有亲戚！
I have an aunt in New York
我有钱，要多少！
I have gold, I can pay
这里将会尸横遍野
There is no one to find here
不要丢下我们不管
They have left us behind here
我必须进去！来人啊！听我说！
I must get in there, listen, anyone
请你告诉我的丈夫，看，这是他的枪
Please tell my husband, look, I have his gun
不要僵持了！让开！
Out of my way if that's all that you've got
越共来了我们会被处决！
If I am here when they come, I'll be shot
让我过去约翰！我不能离开她！
Let me go, John, I can't leave her
我谁都不要！就要她！
Why in the world should I be saved instead of her?
越共会把我们都杀光！
They'll kill who they find here
不要把我们丢下！
Don't leave us behind here
- 让开！ - 你疯了！战争非常残酷！
- Get off!  - It's not you, it's war that's cruel
让他们希望破灭也许是更好的出路
And if some dreams get smashed, perhaps it's best they were
这里将会尸横遍野
There is no one to find here
不要丢下我们不管
They have left us behind here
醒醒吧朋友！我不能让你这么胡来！
Wake up, my friend, your mercy trip has failed
现在已经无济于事，撤离的船已经开走了
There's nothing you can do, that ship has sailed
她并非唯一一个我们丢下的人
She's not the only one we'll have betrayed
快去屋顶，要不就完蛋了
Get to the roof or else we are betrayed
哦，克里斯！
Oh, Chris
我仍然相信
I still believe
你的心，仍然和我连在一起
The heart of you is here with me
我将抓住一切机会，不会放弃！
My heart against all odds holds still
金！
Kim!
求求你！
Please!
你是阳光
You are sunlight
而我是月亮
And I, moon
被命运眷顾
Joined by the gods of fortune
在子夜和正午
Midnight and high noon
共享着天空
That's what we are
就在那一夜
How in one night
我们突然分隔天涯
Have we come so far?
外边，天将破晓
Outside, day starts to dawn
长长的噩梦终于要结束
One long nighttime has gone
你如此靠近
I feel you near
我们如此接近
I reach your place
我知道你就在这
I know you're here
我能摸到你的脸
I touch your face
我们的爱，重新绽放
And our love is reborn
我们爱情的火焰
Brightening the sky
把天空
With the flame
照亮
Of love
我们就是
Made of
阳光
Sunlight
和月亮
Moonlight
金！小金！
Kim. Kim.
我找到克里斯了，就在这间宾馆
I've found Chris. He's at this hotel.
去吧！我照顾小天，这回别搞砸了！
Go! I'll take care of Tam. Don't screw this up.
太棒了！
Yes!
噢！
Oh!
- 对不起  - 不用换床单，谢谢
- I'm sorry.  - Don't turn the bed yet, thank you.
- 我不是服务员  - 哦？那么，有什么事吗？
- I'm not the maid.  - Oh. Well, how can I help you?
- 这是三一七房？ - 是的
- 317?  - Yes.
克里斯多夫·斯科特的房间？
Christopher Scott's room?
哦，天哪，我知道你是谁了
Oh, God, I see. I know who you are.
你一定是小金
You must be Kim
克里斯去找你了
Chris went to find you
请进来
Please come inside
我没有恶意
No one will hurt you
我是克里斯的妻子
I'm Chris's wife
我是艾伦
My name is Ellen.
其实，我是想先见你一面
In a way, I'm glad I'm meeting you first
在这之前，我只听过你的名字
Understand, you were only a name till tonight
我很难想象，咱俩互换位置会什么样
I don't know how I'd feel if our roles were reversed
这不是真的！
Tell me you are lying
我们结婚已经两年了，这是真的，对不起
We've been married two years, I'm sorry, it's true
- 他说他会来找我  - 他说他尽力去找你了
- He said he'd come to get me  - He said he tried to reach you
- 但是他无能为力  - 求你跟我说，这都不是真的！
- But what could he do?  - Please tell me you're not married
你不知道！你无法知道！为了今天我付出了什么！
You don't know, you can't know what I've done to be here
你也理解不了他为什么需要新生活
You don't know how he needed a new start
我全部的希望啊！
I feel walls in my heart closing in
我无法呼吸，我不能相信！
I can't breathe, I can't win
你的孩子，你说他是克里斯的
And your child, you say it's Chris's
是的，女士，我的孩子就是克里斯的
Oh, yes, madame, my son is Chris's
我的孩子不应该过那种生活
I had a dream for my son to belong
那种过街老鼠一般的生活
Not live his life in the street like a rat
我们虽然不富裕，但是我们能尽一切力量帮你们
We aren't rich, but we'll give what we can
我们俩已经谈好了
Chris and I are totally together on that
那你就把小天带走吧
Then you must take Tam with you
把孩子从母亲身边带走？不可能，小金
Take a child from his mother? Impossible, Kim
你必须带小天走！
You must take Tam with you
那样他就能过上我许诺的生活！
Then he'll get what I wanted for him
但是小金啊，孩子需要妈妈
But, Kim, your child needs you
我和克里斯的婚姻里，需要一个我们的孩子
Chris is married to me, we want kids of our own
小天跟你们在一起才能过好！
Tam's chance lies with you now, not with me
- 求你了！ - 不！这不行！
- Please  - No, it won't work
他是你的孩子，不是我的！
He's your child, he's not mine
你这样说，是因为你不是他！
If you're saying that because you made him change his mind
他不会离开我和他的孩子！
Chris must go away and leave me and his son behind
我的丈夫现在成了别人的丈夫！
If you're saying that because my husband has another wife
我的孩子就这样命如尘土！
My child has no future like the dust of life
克里斯今晚来找我，我让他当面的跟我说！
Chris must come tonight to my place, tell me so to my face
小金！小金！
Kim! Kim!
克里斯……
Chris
你现在为什么不在这
Why aren't you here now?
我弄不明白，我现在需要你
I don't understand, I really need you here
求你了
Please
求你帮我
Please, help me
我是否一直在骗自己
Am I fooling myself
是不是我已经失去了你
If I've already lost you?
不，不会的，你还是我的
Nothing's changed, you're still mine
我们可以试着忘了这些
We can try to ignore this
但是如果她回到了你的生命里
But if she has come back in your life
也许，你就不再属于我
Well, then maybe you were never mine
我的心在狂啸
And yet my heart cries maybe
这说不通，这不对劲
It's a trick, it's a lie
她只是在利用你
She's just trying to use you
但我从她的眼神里知道
But I looked in her eyes
失去你她会失去一切
It could kill her to lose you
或许
And maybe
你需要的是她
Just maybe you need her, too
我们认识的时候，你已经颓废不堪
Back when we met you were broken and wild
我整夜抱着你入眠，当你哭喊我也痛苦万分
And I held you at night and I ached when you cried
但是我们排除万难，努力重获新生
But despite what we lacked we tried staying on track
我不后悔
No regret
也许
Yet maybe
是命运把她交还给你
It was fate that suddenly brought her back to you
在我们认识之前，她就比我更懂你
And your love was true love before I even knew you
你想要的生活应该由她来给予
If the life of your dreams is the life she is giving
你们之间的感情，我是否应该退出去
Should I be the one to stop your dream from living?
如果你是她的，那就跟她去，将我遗忘干净
If you're hers, then be hers and forget about me now
原来我一直没有看清
I've been blind for so long
也许我现在应该相信
But perhaps I can see now
也许
And maybe
仅仅是也许
Just maybe
我该坚强的放开手让你随她去
I'll find the strength I need to set you free now
我会坚强，我不会哭泣
I'll be strong, I'll stand firm
我将不会流下泪滴
So my tears won't betray me
但我的心会碎落满地
But my heart might just break
也许
If what may be
May be
我们到处都找不到她
We couldn't find her anywhere
亲爱的，怎么了？
Honey, what's wrong?
小金来过了，我全都告诉她了
Kim was here; the one who had to tell her was me
哦，天哪，我们去的太久了
Oh, my God, I knew we were gone too long
不，我觉得我这么做是十分正确的
No, I think it's exactly what I had to see
你说你只是和她同居
You said you slept with her, that's all you were
但你忘了一件事情，那就是你爱的是她！上帝啊！
Only one thing you left out is that you loved her, God
是的，我们有过感情，但那是好几年前了
Yes, we were in love, but it was years ago
我们分开了
We were torn apart
别解释了，那没用！
Don't explain, there's nothing you can say
她差不多就快崩溃了，她要把孩子给我们
It's like she's gone insane, she tried to give away her own child
- 艾伦  - 你刚才不在
- Ellen  - You weren't here
她的眼睛透露了一切，难道你看不出来吗？
I saw the look in her eyes,don't you see?
她认为你们有婚姻
She thinks she is married to you
- 什么？ - 你必须亲口跟她否认
- What?  - You must tell her she's not
她必须亲耳从你嘴里听到，当然，前提是这都是真的
She must hear it from you! Course, it only depends if it's true
嘿！别胡说了，艾伦！
Hey, don't you doubt me, Ellen
你是我妻子！
You're my wife
那么多士兵在战场上丢了性命
Lots of guys came back and had no life
而且遇见了你
I had you
嘿
Hey.
你随便怎么说，她都给你生孩子了
You can say what you want but she's borne you a son
艾伦
Ellen
你做噩梦的时候喊的是她的名字
In your nightmares, the name that you shouted was hers
- 我知道  - 你都结婚两年了
- I know  - You've been married two years
你从来没对我这样
But not shared things you've done
- 我很抱歉  - 不许！
- I'm sorry  - Don't
不许！别回头！
Don't, don't hold back
看着我！
Let me see
你选择她，还是我！
Is it her now or me?
让我告诉你都发生过什么
Let me tell you the way it was
当我还是从前那个我
Back when I was a different man
当时我不知什么是对，什么是错！
Back when I didn't have a clue what was right
他们把我拖上了船，拉到了越南
They drafted me and shipped me out
参加了一场荒谬的战争
To wind up in that senseless fight
在那里，那场艰难的战争里
There, in the shambles of a war
我找到了我一直在找的
I found what I was looking for
残垣断壁的西贡，只有她才是真实的
Saigon was crazed, but she was real
曾有那么一刻，我感觉到
And for one moment I could feel
一个截然不同的世界
I saw a world I never knew
从她的眼睛里，我感受到了痛苦与折磨
And through her eyes, I suffered too
上帝啊！在那场肮脏的战争里
God, in spite of all the things that were
她是我唯一的寄托！
I started to believe in her
所以我要救她，保护她
So I wanted to save her, protect her
上帝啊！我是个美国人
Christ, I'm an American
我怎么能心安理得！
How could I fail to do good?
我知道我做的一团糟，我们都搞砸了
All I made was a mess, just like everyone else
我们根本没想到在那种地方不可能有奇迹发生
In a place full of mystery that I never once understood
我只是想逃离战争
I wanted back a world I knew
重新和你一起生活
The story of my life began again with you
我现在知道了了
It's all right now
- 不要再说了  - 不，艾伦，我还要告诉你
- That's all through  - No, Ellen, I should have told you
- 我们重新开始，忘掉这些  - 你能相信我吗？
- We'll get past this, start anew  - Will you ever trust me again?
- 我生命里真正需要的  - 我生命里真正需要的
- All I want in my life now  - All I have in my life now
就是你
ls you
嘿，你俩还好吗？
Hey... YOU guys OK?
小金来过了
Kim was here.
天哪，她自己吗？
My God, alone?
是的，在我们出去的时候
Yeah, while we were out looking for her.
- 我需要回避吗？ - 不，不用
- You need some time?  - No, we're OK now.
你们讨论过那个孩子了？
Have you discussed Tam?
那么
Look...
我探访了一个难民营，里面全是战争遗孤
I run a camp that is filled with Boi Doi
他们都在寻找自己的父亲
Looking for the fathers that they may never find
我不禁想，如果小天是我的孩子该怎么办
I don't know what I'd do if Tam were my boy
你们想带他走还是把他留下？
Do you want to take him out or leave him behind?
他是我的孩子，我不会抛弃他
He's my son, I won't abandon him
除了他，上帝啊，还有小金也一起带走
Except that, Jesus Christ, John, there is also Kim
怎么样？
What of her?
如果仅仅是孩子，那就带上吧
If it were only Tam we'd take him now
他是克里斯的孩子，怎么都好说
He's Chris's son, we'd make it work somehow
但是，约翰啊，她心里还是有他
But, John, she still loves him
怎么都不方便啊
How can we have her there?
那就这样，别无选择
There's no choice, I think the answer's clear
就让他俩都待在曼谷，我们资助他们
They'll have to stay in Bangkok, we'll support them here
我觉得这样行
I think this is the answer
你没搞清楚她是怎么想的
You didn't see what's in that girl's head
- 截至目前，我觉得这样可行  - 我希望你们仔细想想
- For now, this is the answer  - I hope you're both proud
你们出的这个办法
Of what you've just said
- 就这样？ - 就这样！
- Is it done?  - It's done
就这样决定了
It's planned
小金不笨，她会明白的
Kim is smart, she'll understand
你必须带走小天
You must take Tam with you
我们会把他送到美国开的学校
In Bangkok, he will go to American schools
我不想违背我许给他的诺言
I won't break my promise to my son
- 他会开始新生活  - 你必须带走小天
- He will start a new life  - You will take Tam with you
- 这样不行！ - 我们提供他们生活所需
- It's not right  - We'll provide for their needs
你俩太单纯了
You're both talking like fools
你不会忘了小天是你的亲骨肉
You won't forget Tam is a part of you
我们这样肯定行！
We will do what is right
对小天好
Right for Tam
对我们好
Right for us
对小金也好
And for Kim
我依然感受到你的温存
I still taste your kisses
你的声音在我耳畔萦绕
Your voice sings in my ear
即使你能忘掉我们的曾经
You can betray what we were yesterday
你今晚也一定会来接走孩子！
But you'll come back tonight for him
嘿！小金
Hey, Kim
拜托，拜托，记住我教给你的
Come on, come on, your recitation
跟他们诉诉苦
Describe your reconciliation
在他发觉上当之前
I hope, before his stimulation
我们三个就能远走高飞了
He bought our little group vacation
他做梦都是梦到我们的孩子
In all his dreams he saw our baby
他教他如何用纸
And he's teaching him to fly
折出纸龙，放飞上天
Paper dragons in the sky
对，是，纸的，但是别忘了现在的状况
Yes, papers, what's the situation?
我们得拿到移民用的绿卡
We'll need our cards for immigration
别耍花样！我可是手眼通天！
No tricks, I've got my reputation
别给我装疯卖傻
Don't want no phony complication
不会，不会
No, no
他今晚会来
He's coming to us tonight
打好你的行装，安排好你的事情
Pack your things, get yourself arranged
我将准备好我最后要做的事情
While I change for my last performance
噢，那我打包啦！
Oh, I'll pack.
我，克里斯和你，这是什么套路啊！
Me, Chris and you? Yeah? What a menage!
曼谷，去你的吧！
Bangkok can screw
开始旅行吧！
bonbon voyage!
我要去美国了
I'm going to America!
我马上就要抽这支雪茄啦
I'm gonna smoke you soon.
我老爸在海防是个纹身师傅
My father was a tattoo artist in Haiphong
但是他在我妈身上可没浪费多少技术
But his designs on Mother didn't last too long
我妈妈出卖肉体，不停地嚼着槟榔
My mother sold her body, high on betel nuts
哦…
Oh...!
而我就负责把那些乡巴佬都领过来
My job was bringing red-faced messieurs to our huts
推销自己的老妈虽说是个悲剧
Selling your mom is a wrench
可香水却能遮盖臭气
Perfume can cover a stench
法国人都这么干
That's what I learned from the French
后来奠边府那边大不如前了
Then it all changed with Diem Ben Pu
- 法国蛤蟆回了老家，别人又来啦？ - 谁啊？
- The Frogs went home; who came?  - Guess who?
我们都发疯了，但不要吃惊
Are you surprised we went insane
因为美元像雨一样落下来了
With dollars pouring down like rain?
生意人从来不会来硬的
Businessmen never rob banks
因为我就算卖屎都能获得个好名声
I can sell shit and get thanks
至于这个嘛，美国人都是这么干哒
Now, that's what I learned from the Yanks
我的人生并不忙碌
I'm fed up with small-time hustles
因为我的聪明，全用来赚钱啦
I'm too good to waste my talent for greed
我想找个地方放松下筋骨
I need room to flex my muscles
一条大鱼在大海里才能满足
In an ocean where the big sharks feed
成全我吧！美国佬！
Make me Yankee
你们才是我的家人
They're my family
我们都是贩卖梦想的行家！
We're selling dreams people need
空气里是什么味道？
What's that I smell in the air?
就是美国梦啊！
The American dream
未来的百万富翁
Sweet as a new millionaire
就是美国梦啊！
The American dream
粉墨登场吧！
Pro-packed and ready to wear
我的美国梦啊！
My American dream
就像拿起蛋糕
Fat like a chocolate eclair
一口吸出奶油一样甜蜜
As I...suck out the cream
来啊！西贡小姐！
Au reservoir, Miss Saigon
我准备好了！
I'm moving on
抓住这个转瞬即逝的机会
Grab what you can till it's gone
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
阴险的中国人毁了我的好日子
Greasy Chinks make life so sleazy
到了美国，我要办一个四星级的俱乐部
In the States,I'll have a club that's four-starred
像我这种人在美国一定吃得开
Men like me there have things easy
我要聘一个律师，还要一个保镖
I'll have a lawyer and a bodyguard
做着生意，玩儿着漂亮妞
To the johns there, I'll sell blondes there
这一切只要刷卡就行啦！
That they can charge on a card
刷刷
Th k-ts k!
哦，空气中的味道，那是……
Oh, what's that I smell in the air?
我的美国梦啊
The American dream
豪华的就像总统套房
Sweet as a suite in Be Air
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
姑娘们的胸一个比一个大呀！
Girls can buy tits by the pair
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
秃头们梦想着茂密的头发！
Bald people think they'll grow hair
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
不管！什么！贴个标签！就拿出去卖！
Asses that stick out to there
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
撑死胆大的！
You can take more if you dare
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
银行大把的印钱啊
Banks print money from air
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
可卡因！散弹枪！还有虔诚的信徒！
Cocaine, shotgun and prayer
我的美国梦啊！
The American dream
哈里路亚！
Hallelujah
啤酒一口喝干
Schlitz down the drain
再开一瓶香槟
Pop the champagne
现在我们都来狂欢吧！我的美国梦啊！
It's time we all entertainmy American dream
来吧！姑娘们！
I want my girls
你们还喜欢这些羽毛吧！
Don't you just love the feathers?
给你们的干爹一个吻吧！
Blow your big daddy a kiss!
下来！
Oh, come on down.
谁是这里的女王？
I want to see my queen of the town.
过来吧，闪耀登场！
Come on, baby. Rise and shine.
过来吧，过来吧，不管你在哪
Come out, come out, wherever you are.
她真的存在！她真的存在！
She's alive! She's alive!
看看啊！她多么美丽啊！
Look at her. Isn't she beautiful?
不得了的姑娘，她需要了不得的小伙儿！
She's a big girl. She needs big boys.
- 你们好啊，小伙儿？ - 耶！耶！
- Hello, boys!  - Yeah! Yeah!
你们都很了不得嘛？就像美国那样？
You guys are big. American big.
你们能搞定她们吧？
Think you can handle her?
我爱你宝贝！我爱你！
I love you, lady, I love you.
你让我热泪盈眶！
You make me moist.
我们都是性感的荡妇！不是吗！
We're just sexy bitches, aren't we?
赢家！赢家！
Winner, winner!
耶！
yeah!
不顾一切的放纵吧！
Live like you haven't a care
你的美国梦啊！
The American dream
再放纵也没关系
Take even more than is fair
你的美国梦啊！
The American dream
这些够精彩吗？可我还没玩够呐！
Is this too much? I can never tell.
时代广场上美女成行！
Call girls are lining Times Square
- 你的美国梦啊！ - 你觉得我还有更精彩的？
- The American dream  - You think I know different?
腰缠万贯的流浪汉
Bums there have money to spare
你的美国梦啊！
The American dream
用金钱来填满你的空虚
Spend when the cupboard is bare
你的美国梦啊！
The American dream
出卖你的灵魂和一切，就是你的美国梦啊！
Just sell your soul and you gain,the American dream
说说！你看到了什么？
Say, can you see?
自由的国度！
Land of the free
必须哒！
Sure can
马上你们就能从我这里学到经验
Soon you will buy it from me
我的美国……
The American...
梦啊！梦啊！梦啊！梦啊！
Dream! Dream! Dream! Dream!
嘿！
Hey!
我的钱都哪去了？
Where's my money going?
你们都去哪了？快回来！
Where are you guys going? Come back!
我刚进入状态啊！
It was just getting good.
是不是很精彩？
Wasn't that fabulous?
那就是我闻到的！
That's what I smell in the air
我的美国梦啊！
My American dream
噢！
Oh!
来吧，小天，勇敢的孩子
Now, Tam, my brave boy
漫长的等待结束了
Our long wait has ended
笑一笑，孩子，你马上就有父亲了
Smile, Tam, for you have a father at last
他来接你回家
He has come to take you home
接你到那个我一直跟你说的地方
All I dreamed for you he'll do
你永远是我的孩子
You're still mine
我不会自己苟活
But I can't go along
不要悲伤，我会一直照看着你，就在那遥远的地方
Don't be sad; though I'm far away, I'll be watching you
这是别离的时刻
This is the hour
我终于等到了
I swore I'd see
漫长的等待
I alone can tell now
注定的结局
What the end must be
他们为你选定命运
They think they'll decide your life
我将把它交给你
No, it will be me
孩子，再看我一次吧
Look at me one more time
记住妈妈的模样
Don't forget what you see
妈妈再亲你一下吧
One more kiss
我们将永远分离
And then say goodbye
金！
Kim!
小金啊！上帝啊
Kim! Oh, my God!
你为什么要这么做啊！
What have you done, Kim?
为什么！
Why?
神明已经把小天带给了你
The gods have guided you to your son
上帝啊！
Oh, Jesus!
求求你，不要死！
Please, don't die
抱住我
Hold me
最后一次
One last time
我抱住了
I've got you.
就在那一夜
How in one night
我们如此接近
Have we come so far?
嘿！
Hey.
金！
Kim.
金啊！
Kim!
不！金！
No! Kim!
字幕制作｜猫科夫
Subtitles: Mokov
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者